People are still walking in.
Yeah.
But that's okay. Okay, should
we start?
So,
good morning, everyone. I think we're almost ready to
start.
Just a few things for the speakers.
We will give you about
12 minutes for your talk and two minutes for questions.
We have these nice cards that show you how much time, at five minutes, two minutes,
and when time's up. We're going to try to be quite strict on this, that when
people are switching between sessions that they can still follow
this.
Without further waiting, I will happy to introduce to
you David Williamson, who will give you an introduction session to this AI
for Biodiversity Data session, and
have fun.
Thank you, Martin. Thank you, Elena. Oh, do I need to stand away?
Yes. Welcome, everybody. Thank you for coming along this morning, first
thing. So
just to get started, I wanted to let you know this session will be in two
parts. We have this session that you're in, and after the break,
we will be back here again for the second half of the session.
And the same group which organized this session organized a panel discussion
on Thursday.
So please, if you are interested in being critical about
AI and biodiversity research, come along to that.
We have a really nice group of speakers that you can see down here.
So
I hope this is not too basic for this audience, but I wanted to think a little bit
about what exactly we mean by AI and give a very brief
introduction to a few
important concepts. So AI, as most of you probably know, is
quite an older field at this point.
It goes back to the 1960s, arguably much earlier than
that, too.
But in this session, I think most of the speakers will be talking about machine
learning, which is a subfield in AI.
And
when we talk about machine learning, we think about a whole bunch of things,
decision trees, random forests, so on.
But again, we're thinking mainly now about what we call deep learning,
which includes neural networks and transformers and large language models, as
we'll get into with the speakers later.
But very briefly, what-
... is the problem of ML? What are we trying to do in machine learning?
And I think we can consider this to be solving this one equation,
y is f of x, where we don't know what f is.
So we have some inputs, and we want to find out what's the output meant
to be, and that varies by problem.
And we approximate the function by throwing lots and lots
of examples at a model of some sort, and we
end up with an approximation for f that lets us make predictions on
further unknown y's. And I'll show you an example so this makes
more sense maybe. So here's an example from my own work.
We have a picture of a herbarium sheet.
It has this nice specimen on it, and we want to know, are there buds in this
picture? Are there flowers? Are there fruits?
And you can imagine there's some function, perhaps a well-defined function, which
can give us this answer from this image, but we don't know that function.
So we have a neural network which tries to estimate or
approximate the function to give us a good prediction
for are there buds, are there flowers, are there fruits.
And this is maybe an example of training data.
You have lots and lots of images in this case, and each of them is annotated
saying if there's fruit, if there's buds, if there's flowers, and we throw this
into the neural network. We train.
We hopefully do something a little bit clever in the background, and eventually, we
get our answer like this. So it has predicted buds, flowers, fruits.
It's more or less right.
So hopefully, that's how it works.
But I think one thing we'll be talking about a lot in this session, certainly we
talked about it last year in Tadwigg, and is
maybe a big topic of discussion in the general discussion too,
are large language models.
So very briefly, large language models.
These are, I think I would like to call it an advance in natural language
processing,
based on transformers. And I think it's possible to argue that they are
qualitatively different from previous machine learning
models in that they speak to us, which I think is something
which a lot of people find very striking, very surprising, that you are not just
looking at numbers or XML files, but rather you're getting natural language
responses to your natural language queries.
I think their performance is very hard to measure.
It's easy to say intuitively, is it doing a good job when
you're speaking with one, but hard to measure in an objective way.
And of course, they require huge amounts of training data. They're very expensive.
This is a problem that we're all aware of, I think.
Oh, a blank slide.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, so these large language models, basically what they do is predict the next
word, and they've been trained on a huge corpus.
People say all human knowledge, that's an exaggeration, but quite a lot of
written human text at least. And they also solve this problem,
y is f of x.
And here, for example, of a standard sentence that you would find in the training
corpus, "It was the day my grandmother exploded."
And you might start with it as an input, "It was the day my grandmother,"
and you ask what's the next word or what's the next token in this
sentence. And of course, here, as we all know, it's exploded, followed by a
full stop, followed by an end of sentence marker.
And so if the model guessed these, it would be marked correct because that's what's
in the training data. But of course, you can also choose different x,
different inputs, and then based on the training data,
which is many sentences like this, where you cover up part of the
sentence, you have the model guess, you show it the answer,
it can find some plausible output.
And this is what we see in the chat box as well.
You get a system prompt, which is just a bunch of words at the start.
You get the user prompt, which is you saying, "Hey, what's the capital of
Norway?"
You get the conversation so far, if there is one previously, and the
large language model looks at its own input as well when predicting the next word.
So what's the capital of Norway? Hopefully, it says Oslo, and then it knows
this in the conversation. That's what we call the context window.
So it will predict the next word based on all of this previous context.
And that's it. That's all they do.
It's really impressive, I think. It's really surprising that we get this very
natural-feeling conversation from something which conceptually at least is very
simple. Of course, there's a lot of exciting, interesting maths in
the background. How do you do the weighting?
There's a bunch of bolt-ons where you can have them call Python functions or
whatever, but in essence, that's what a large language model does and what it is.
And if you have a reasoning model, that means it prompts itself again and
again with some additional instructions like this, but there's
no actual reasoning in the sense that we have it, I would say.
Maybe that's a philosophical question, but I feel comfortable making that claim.
And the one thing I wanted to finish on this topic is
what we call hallucinations, which is basically where we say, "It's made something
up. This isn't true."
But as you've seen, it's just a word predictor. It doesn't know what's true.
It doesn't reason. It doesn't think.
So
if we start with a sentence, "Hymenoptera is a" something, and you
ask
how do you complete this sentence? I did this.
So here's one large language model, Hymenoptera, large order of insects,
and so on. I think any entomologists in the audience will agree with this
statement.
I tried a different model. It gives you a similar answer.
But then we can also ask ourselves, if we are trying
to measure performance here, is one of these answers better than the other?
How would you decide?
These words are all fine. They're in the right order, roughly.
There's a grammatical mistake in the second one.
But in general, these are fine answers.
The words presumably are likely in the distribution.
So how would you score these two?
And the third example,
I think that's fair to say.
I lied. I said I was writing a book on Nordic cuisine.
And it gave me this response. But again, it's a perfectly nice sentence.
It could be true.
It probably is true, actually. I guess you can eat ants.
But that's probably not what we're looking for in the context of a biodiversity
research session. So is that a bad answer?
Is it a hallucination? I don't know.
And this last one,
you don't know. Maybe. Maybe it's happening.
So this could be a hallucination, or this could be a true fact, and there's
no way that you can tell from the text.
So there's no objective way, I would argue,
to rank these things, to measure the outperformance here.
So I don't have any conclusion there.
That's just some food for thought when we're talking about these things today.
And I'll wrap up now because I want to get onto the actual exciting part of the
session,
with just some examples of the kinds of things we'll be hearing about today.
We have quite a few talks on machine vision and on
neural networks. We'll be talking about audio-based processing of
data,
where AI transcription is a really exciting topic that I'm interested to hear more
about today, and we also have some people talking about validation.
We have some people on theory, some people who have actual things they've done in
the real world, in the field. So I'm really excited to hear the
talks today, and I think I'll leave it there.
So we have our first speaker coming up.
Thank you very much.
Would you like to-
Okay, so our next speaker is Rachael Wiles.
Thank you.
Okay.
Perfect. I'll just wait for the slides to do their thing.
Great to meet you all. Thank you so much for having me this early in the
morning. I'm going to start off with quite a nice lightweight
presentation for yous to digest while you finish your morning coffee,
just around AI and how we're using that to build some
production-ready systems that we have at the museum.
So yeah, like I said, my name's Rachael Wiles.
This is my first ever TadWig, so I'll take a little opportunity to
just introduce myself as well.
The first time I
got to grips with biodiversity and applied machine learning to it
was actually back in my dissertation.
I was with
a program you might know on the BBC called "Springwatch," where we were
doing bounding boxes to try and detect animals so the poor cameraman wouldn't have
to point a camera at a bird box for hours and hours and hours on end.
They could automate some of that system.
So that was way back when I was doing my master's.
I then left academia to go into industry, where I worked
for Microsoft and AWS, as a consultant
with them.
And what I was doing was bringing these AI concepts into the
public sector and learning how we can do some AI
transformation, excuse me, to, yes, really
bring people up to speed with how that works.
And now I'm back at the museum,
working on a product called the Data Ecosystem, which is a whole talk in and of
itself. So I will introduce some of those concepts, but if you want
to learn more about the product that I'm building,
please come find me at the end of the session.
Very happy to chat through that further.
This talk is going to focus more on the how we're building it and the tools that
we're using
to put that in place.
Yeah, so like I said, what we'll be going over is what we're building, how we're
working with AI, a couple of notes on humans in the loop, and
then last parting thoughts of where I'd
like some input from you and some guidance from you.
I've really enjoyed the presentations that we saw yesterday, and I'm sure there'll
be more exciting content coming up over the course of the week.
And I want to take those learnings back with me, so I'll be specific on
those.
So the Data Ecosystem is a biodiversity
platform for predominantly urban nature, but we
also have some community science data coming in from all over the UK.
And we are pulling that data all into one place, data warehousing
it,
making sure it's gold standard by various data quality checks.
We're including eDNA, environmental sensing,
community science data, camera trap data.
There's lots all coming into one place.
It's part of a partnership that we're developing with AWS, which is in its
fourth year now.
And just to be clear, we had no AWS
capabilities at the museum before we worked on this piece.
So as part of this, we've had to put in some foundational
work to get there and build on ambitious products like this.
So also keen to talk to anyone who has murmurings about the
foundations that you need before AI get there.
I've got lots to say on that matter, so come find me if you'd like.
Yeah, never built on this before. We are a very tiny,
full-time tech team. We've had consultants that have come in and helped with
this.
There's a data engineer, senior engineer, and me, who and I personally
haven't touched code for many years, and I don't think I should.
So I don't know if I can even count myself as a technical member of staff.
But nevertheless, we're a tiny team with big gaps, so we don't have
something that you might get a wider organization around.
Data quality engineers, test engineers,
front-end engineers. We've
used consultants for that in the past, or others in the museum that are willing to
help. UI, UX, there's pieces that are missing, and we need to plug those
gaps, and I wouldn't be surprised if many of you in the room are thinking that you
also don't have those functions in your organizations.
And then we have a lot of demand on the platform.
So 10 million records in its first six months of the platform going
live.
There's a lot going on there, so we need to make sure that it is Scalable,
manageable, and easy for us to integrate and adapt as we
go forward, and we hopefully don't break things. That's always the goal.
So yeah, I've gone over this. I'll fly over this in a couple of
details. So yeah, records gathered over time
for our research scientists, and it must keep
respecting the security and governance baselines that
we want to make sure we're operating in within the remit of the museum.
So we don't want to go ahead and overreach on the AI policy.
And we want to make sure that it's a trust environment for our researchers.
And then how we work with AI,
I think I'm trying to work out if it's a sector specific thing or if it's just a
very British thing where I think some people are nearly embarrassed
about admitting that they use AI tools in their day-to-day.
So I'm hoping to demystify some of that, encourage a bit of conversation around
how we go with that.
By no means am I saying that use these tools, these tools are
the ones that you should be using, but these are the ones that we personally employ
within the teams.
And there are three distinct boundaries that we use when we're creating them.
So Claude Design, if you haven't checked it out, I'd thoroughly
recommend it for prototyping purposes.
You can build extremely complex UI frameworks
within them, and it's really helped me have conversations with
researchers, end users about some of their more complex
requirements and how that would actually transform into a tech
platform.
The number of times in the past where I've had these conversations, they've ended
up in a requirement sheet, which is just a text document.
And then we've got to actually delivering the first iteration of the product, and
they say, "I actually thought that in my head it looked like
something slightly different."
If you are able to mock up a quick UI or a quick
PowerPoint slide or whatever it might be within Claude, it's a great place to
start because you can go ahead and tweak that, and then you have a really good idea
of what you're building before you even go and build it.
So thoroughly recommend looking at it.
Not using any museum IP or real records there,
so you can just put your schemas, your table headings perhaps into
Claude. It will generate loads of dummy data for you.
So you don't need to worry about
putting your production data or your precious data
into Claude if you don't want to. It will generate that for you.
And then a really good handoff point for that, which brings us onto the middle one,
is you can then say, from the prototype that we've just mocked up, can we
go ahead and create some front-end code to go
ahead and develop on that?
And that then gets passed off to developers to go ahead and use.
We're using AWS Quero, which I don't think that many
people will know in the room, but it allows you to interface
with some of the LLMs that are really well known.
This is a great code assistance IDE tool,
and it's also able to run within the AWS
account. So if you're thinking about governance, security, giving
people access to models that you're not sure of, or being able
to control what data access has, it is really
useful that it sits within that AWS account so you can capture the
logs, you can control the access centrally.
There's lots of perks to doing that, and it just happens to be that the rest of the
platform sits on AWS, so it's a natural fit for our developers
to use. So they're going ahead and developing using that.
We're then using various GitLab agents in the way that
we
develop and deploy our code. So these are integrated
testing pieces that go ahead and perform
checks on the code, make sure that it's okay, really add that sort
of reviewer piece in. We do
get the team of two to check each other's code as well,
but quite frankly, there are some tasks that can very easily be
automated.
So that's a great last-minute stop to go ahead and
check some code before you then deploy it.
So we have those sort of three boundaries to how we're using AI.
And I will say that this is great for prototyping.
If you're then moving onto a production-ready system, you're starting to
think about your boundaries of dev, test, and prod, and the different flavors that
you might want to apply there.
This is our
mini tenants that we've set up. We obviously have an AI-wide
museum policy. If your organization doesn't have an AI
policy, now is the time to get one.
It's much easier to influence than help build an
AI policy from the beginning, so get involved in those conversations if there's one
coming.
But what I would do as well is--
It's really hard to also retrofit
your code or whatever it is that you're doing to an AI policy, so
good to go with that.
These are some of our team rules. We don't want AI to
act on the real thing, especially if it's just a developer tool.
We want to keep that production data safe and in its own environment for now.
We don't want AI to reach beyond its limits, so we don't want it
to--
Coming onto the next one, we don't want to affect a neighboring project as well.
We want to make sure that it knows what it has access to, knows the
influence that it can make, and make decisions from there.
Promote prototype code unrewritten.
We're allowing this in dev only. So, we
will continue to
go ahead and allow our engineers to make direct changes to dev with the AI
because we know that we now have those boundaries set up between our dev
environment, our test environment, our production environment.
If you don't have that, don't do that.
And then we don't want to bend the data model to a mock-up.
We want to make sure the data model stays set.
And we don't want AI to suddenly suggest, "Why don't you just change the
data model?" No, we know what we want our data model to be. We have that.
So these are some rules that we've put in place.
I've only got two minutes left, so I'm going to absolutely fly through this, but
humans in the loop.
A few statements on how we want to make sure that the
AI-assisted output, when it arrives for humans, it arrives as
a suggestion that they can then go ahead and action if they'd like.
We have various components that we're building in the data ecosystem
that, especially for our community science workflows, they're going to
provide things like duplicate detection,
human detection in images, so we can do PII checks,
and also clustering of similar species.
And these things will be surfaced to users to be able
to make decisions on how their verification workflow goes.
But
the main
users of this at the moment are our internal users in the Centre for UK Nature.
They are the experts. AI is not going to outperform how
good they are at verifying this data.
So we can help them along the way and make it super easy in our workflows to do
that.
So this is the current mock-up of how we're doing that.
On the left there, if you were to scroll down, you can see that
all of the information that is in a verified record is
shown to a user. And then on the right here, this is where the
user goes through to make their verification.
And so duplicate detection, clustering,
and PII data removal will be available as a tool in the right-hand
side there for users to make an identification of that
record.
So very human in the loop, which is the stance that we will continue
to take for current development.
So what is working and what is not? We're able to work with PACE with a boundary.
But the big question we have at the moment is about validation and
provenance.
So if you have any ideas on how we can make sure
that within all this AI work that we're doing, we can maintain the original
record, who did it, what did it, so we can trace that back to users so they get
appropriate credit
and citations for their work, then that would be really great.
And yeah, further guidance on AI services and
a shared public sector position on how we want to go ahead and use this
is always something that I'm keen to talk about, but I have run out of time,
so I will stop there.
Have we got a minute or so for questions? Maybe we do.
Any questions, anyone?
Are there any questions? We have time for one or two questions.
Thank you so much.
You showed three tools actually, and I was wondering what's your
favorite like?
Well, personally, as a product manager, I really like Claude.
And Claude Design is the one that I like to use for wireframes.
I think if you could pick one that encompasses a lot of the things that you might
want to do, you can take things from Claude Design into Claude Code and
then use that. I've also had
great
interest in tweaking their models.
You can give the models descriptions, and then you can also go and choose which
model you'd like to use. I found that some of them have quite different ways of
speaking back to you. So the Opus models are,
in my opinion, rather chatty. Whereas if you were to go onto the Fable
model, they're really quite direct, and this is how it is.
So I think your way of working and how you like to interact with
it, you can play around with that a lot more in Claude.
But you can access Claude models through things like Keiro, so it's not just
bound to Claude Design, but I do like the UI that's there as well.
So that's my personal preference.
Thank you.
No worries.
Okay. We have no more time, but keep your questions.
The speakers are around, so we can do it after, during the
break.
Thank you.
Then it's my pleasure to introduce to you the next speaker from
Montpellier, Giulio Martellucci, if I pronounce it correctly.
And
we're going to
learn about scalable edge AI.
Please.
You hear me?
Yes.
Okay, great. So,
I will present to you specific solution for tracking
invasive species in roadside imagery.
So first of all, to give a bit of context,
invasive plant species is actually one of the top five
major drivers of biodiversity loss and ecosystem
disruption as they pose a critical
threat for native species, habitats, and ecosystem
functioning.
In particular, transportation corridors, such as highways or railways,
are considered
accelerate the dispersal of the seeds
across landscapes and over long distances.
And for this reason, it is important to
making practice
real-time
monitoring for
facilitate the early detection and the intervention for these
alien species and trying to map
their abundance
overall.
So
with this aim within the Biodiversa+
project,
embedded camera was mounted on vehicles in order to capture
high-resolution roadside images
across different countries, as you can see here, at high speed
and
trying to minimize
blur effect.
So the system tries to monitor 60 alien species and
cover nearly 2,200 kilometers of roads,
creating a massive
number of images that has been analyzed.
So
for example, here we
try to see how to adapt
plant species identifiers that is trained on single species
images, but focus mainly on
organs and try to adapt it to
community species imagery. So a simple yet
effective solution
has been shown being the multi-scale tiling, for example,
where
the high-resolution image is cropped with different tiles
of different dimension. The classifier is applied to each
of these tiles, and then predictions are aggregated with max
pooling in order to get
presence-absence signals of the
species present in the image. However, this solution, as
you can imagine, is very costly. We measure that with the
current plant API, it takes
nearly 10 seconds to analyze an image,
and that resulted on for covering the all monitor
roads
at nearly 70 days nonstop. So we need
a more scalable and cost-effective solution.
To do with this aim, we leverage the
common machine learning technique called knowledge distillation in order to train
a global multi-label model that takes an
input directly
the high-resolution image. So originally, the
knowledge distillation
consists on a student model that tries to mimic
the behavior of the more complex teacher, where here the
prediction are made with the multi-scale tiling and the
classifier not restricted to alien species, but at the world
flora of
nearly 70,000
plant species.
So at the first step, the student is exactly the
same model used for tiling and is
unfrozen.
So it's the PlantNet model that importantly is a Dinov2
vision transformer model, the state of the art
nowadays for computer vision application.
And it is fine-tuned on 22 millions
plant images. However, could not be optimal for high-resolution
monitoring since its inference complexity is
quadratic with respect to the image resolution because
of the self-attention mechanism of the patches.
For this reason, we further distilled the
global model to another
model with another architecture, the ConvNeXt one.
And in this case, it's
a Dinov3, so it's pre-trained, and it could
be
more optimal for our
use case
since ConvNeXt, thanks to its convolutional
operation, it scales linearly with the image
resolution.
So we trained the model
for 400,000
images that corresponds to one
image every three frames, with the V100
GPUs. And initially, it was trained on the
original input resolution, 418, and then fine-tuned
over a few epochs,
while the ConvNeXt model is directly fine-tuned on the
higher resolution. So as you can see, the ConvNeXt model
achieves the best
results for computational efficiency.
For example, it employed less than
92 times of GFLOPS compared to the tiling
solution. And while the tiling solution needs three
seconds per image, the ConvNeXt
analyze 14
images per second.
And overall, for example, for covering all the
monitor roads, the multi-scale tiling would have been needed
18 days,
consuming 138 kilowatt hours, while the
ConvNeXt solution just
would need 12 hours and consuming just
2.6 kilowatt hours.
In term of results,
as you can see, the ConvNeXt model
also
achieves the best solution on a
test
set where the
alien species are annotated by
experts, and it contains 36 monitors
plant species, where several
alien species can also be included in the same image.
So it achieves the best solution for
two metrics, the mean average precision and also the IoU
ROC.
You can appreciate that the tilling
still ranks true occurrence
correctly, but
makes too many false alarms. And while the
model trained on the 1518
resolution is not enough for fine-grained
applications.
Also,
by analyzing Grad-Cams of the vision transformer model, we can see
that thanks to this sequential analysis
of the images, the model has great capacity
on both identifying, but also detecting the position
of the species
in this very complex image with
occlusion and overlapping species, and also
analyze dense features,
the projection on 3D dimension
of dense features. We can see that it
greatly separates overlapping species with
the background.
So to conclude, we have seen
mainly that citizen science imagery can support
large-scale, efficient, and lightweight plant biodiversity
monitoring, and that ConvNeXt models are the
best solution
for this type of application.
We have learned that it could be used for real-time
monitoring, and also that
he was able to capture the organ-specific
plant information and replicate it on very
complex
imagery.
Importantly, we aim to make this model open source
that
hopefully it can reduce the need to
store and process these massive volumes of
imagery and can extend the
monitoring capacity on different roads.
In terms of perspective, we aim to extend
the training on more plant community imagery.
For example, drone
images or even the citizen science
image
captured by users.
Yeah. Or plot images like here, and trying to
capture a greater range of biodiversity
overall.
We could also aim to extend
this monitoring also for railways
corridors.
And, yeah, not but least, we aim to
continue developing this solution in the Beagle European
project. So thank you very much, and happy to answer to your
questions.
Hello. So thank you, Giulio, for that.
We have time for maybe one or two more questions if anyone has
any.
Okay.
Thanks a lot. Concerning you extending the monitoring
to railways, have you considered monitoring as well on rivers
because they are usually invasive corridors?
Yeah, of course.
Rivers is also another
place where it could be very interesting for capturing
plant species, and
in a very long perspective, will be very nice to
really
evaluate the models on all the plants
contained in the images and not only for invasive
species.
We have time for one more question if anyone has any.
I had a random question, actually, if I can ask one, which was
how well was the model working depending on the growth of the plant?
Depending on?
On the growth of the plant. Did you see it working less well, for
example, if it was less grown, or did you see any differences depending on how
well-grown it was?
So
I think results depend
both on the number of images that are correctly
annotated
by experts and also the size of the plants.
I guess
it working a bit better for trees than
medium species that are very hard to be captured
in very high
resolution images.
Okay. Thank you. Okay. Let's give Giulio another round of applause.
Thank you.
Welcome.
So our next speaker is Reiter Ngimapi from NIBIO,
who is going to be talking about AI systems for integrated pest management.
Hello. Okay.
Okay. Good morning, everyone. My name is Reiter Ngimapi from NIBIO.
My presentation is about
an idea or a reflection we had,
and we decided to come and share the idea and the challenge we are
facing.
So on behalf of the team from NIBIO,
I work at NIBIO as a
research scientist focusing on
Understanding the interaction between
insect, the pests, and their natural environment, like
in relation to climatic condition.
So I'm going to present a vision for
integrated management of pest insects and their natural enemy.
And what you can see on the image is an example of
natural interaction happening
on the plant in the field, where you can see
another some type of insect
that are attacking other for protecting the
plant
and help protecting the plant. So,
for context,
the International Society of Precision Agriculture
define precision agriculture like
the management strategy that account for spatial and temporal
variability to improve the sustainability
of agricultural production.
And to be able to
implement that strategy,
that rely more on the use of
advanced tool like GPS,
remote sensing,
and remote sensing to collect, handle, and manage a lot of
information and data.
And
when we talk about
crop production, one important aspect is the protection of
the plant.
And
in order to achieve plant protection,
there's
a framework called Integrated Pest Management that consists of using
different tool
available to keep the pest population below a certain level.
And within that framework, there's an approach that we call
conservation biological control.
And the particularity of the conservation biological control is the
practice that consists of modifying farm environment
and management routine to protect and support
existing population of natural beneficial organism.
So if you put those two concepts together, the focus is to maintain the
biodiversity,
keep an
environmentally
friendly
field, and
solidify or strengthen the resilience of the farm.
Now, the question is: How
can we
manage to integrate
precision agriculture into biological control?
In Norway, for example,
NIBIO under its
center for precision agriculture in collaboration with other partner, like
Kilt and others,
a lot of advancement have been achieved in precision
weed control.
So many advancement are made, and one of the
key solution, or one of the most innovative solution that
was put in place recently is the development of those
precision sprayer robot.
What is the particularity of the robot is that
when they scan
a farm and differentiate between the crop and the weeds,
once
they
successfully detect the weeds,
instead
of broadcast spraying like it's commonly done,
the technology just
lay some drop of the herbicide on the top of the leaves.
It
had contribute to reduce
in Norway, the solution have been so successful because the regulation, for
example, in Norway, we are not allowed,
for example, to use drone to spray fungicides.
And that is why this solution has been quite successful because
it managed to reduce the use
of herbicide for between 40% to 90%.
So that is where our reflection came.
If we consider that solution we have, and now we have
under the framework of conservation biological control, where
the goal is to
control the plant, kill
the pest, while maintaining the other
beneficial organism. How can we
extend this solution so that when the robot move, it can
still detect the pest and differentiate it from the beneficial organism, and just
lay the drop of insecticide at the top of the insect?
So that was the idea. And
when we
had this idea, we thought that,
okay.
Sorry, as I was explaining,
so this is basically where we are now.
We are working. How can we reach to this solution?
Where, like you see here, you have what we call, for example, a
parasitoid that is attacking a pest.
So this
is familiar, what we consider as beneficial organism.
Usually, you have that interaction into the farm.
And then our question was then: How can we move from here to here?
The first idea that came into our mind was maybe we can
use transfer learning, where we just
go and collect some data from
the field where that interaction exists and follow
the step of what most of you may know about
adopting. Then when we started to do that, the first thing was
then to collect the
representative data set image
And then we realized that they were more difficult than we thought.
Because unlike
weeds, that are because when we consider, we say the precision show
take into account the spatial and temporal state. The weeds are static.
So when we try to
collect the image, the first thing when identify the right timing for
detecting the pest on the field. Because working in collaboration with extension
official, by the time we receive the information, okay, we are facing some attack.
By the time we
reach to the
field and expect to collect the picture, there is not any more
that interaction we are looking for.
Either the pest is not present or either the damage are
already present. The second challenge was that
the insect are mobile, so they are dynamic.
And
for most of the pest,
the damaging phase that you are targeting, for example, the eggs and larva,
they lay on the underside of the leaf.
Then the question was then, what
could be the easiest way or the most adapted approach to
collect the picture? And the third challenge we have was
identifying
the most appropriate equipment, like the camera and that thing, that
are cost-effective. Because the idea at the end of the day, you need to
have a solution that is not that expensive.
And also,
when we have solution, we have to also
make sure that it fit under the country regulation because sometime a lot of the
solution or the possibility, for example, if you want
to settle your environment where you can take the picture, the controlled
environment, you are not, for example, allowed to release certain type of
natural enemy to create that interaction. That make it difficult.
Then you
have
to find a way where you can still collect your image without
crossing the border.
So that
was the
main challenge.
That are some of the challenge we
are facing now. And
our priority now, as we are explaining, we are currently trying
exploring different type of
approach.
Now,
we try first on the field, it was not successful.
We are exploring the possibility to create a controlled environment, but even that
is not that simple. But we are still thinking, we
are exploring idea, and I don't know, maybe here someone can make a
suggestion that could help us have that environment where we have
or a specific tool or equipment that can help us to,
for example, be able to take picture of pests under the leaf,
capturing those type of interaction.
So that was
the core of my presentation, and
we are still thinking. As I said, it's a work in
process,
we are still working on it, and we just wanted to share the idea and the
ongoing work with you. So that is, I will end by thanking some of
my
partner and colleague that are collaborating on this topic.
So that is all what I have for
you today. Thank you.
Thank you very much, and thank you for being so much in time.
So we have some time for questions now.
Are there any questions that you want to ask?
I have a question. So you already have the camera set up to
at the top view, so you can look at the weeds.
So is the idea that you'll integrate the AI system
within that view, and then in addition to that, you'll have a secondary
camera looking at the bottom of the leaf?
Or are you looking for something more flexible, so it's just one camera, but it
moves?
One camera. No. Okay.
Unfortunately, as you bring, the partner tool that we have,
they have a certain trawler. That is why initially, that is what they commonly
use to collect. So at the certain frequency,
when you
drive that in the field, it take picture at a certain frequency.
It was perfect.
Initially, it was designed for, let's say, for the weeds because
when the trawler was going,
regardless of the picture, they could capture either the weeds or the crop, and
then they can feed the model. But when now you come to insects,
first you need first a
specific picture of the plant, and then you need to be able
also to capture the insect orientation.
So the trawler was not
well adapted. We use that. The picture was not that
good. So that is why we started to consider
alternative solution.
Any more questions?
I was just wondering about speed of the model, because I imagine with
picking out weeds, I don't know how fast this trolley moves when it's
picking out weeds. How quickly does the model need to
identify the weeds? And I guess that is, yeah, a real challenge
with insects and pests that are moving.
And I guess another question is which sort of architectures are you
using for the, like, what's the base model architecture, and have you
looked at other
maybe faster options?
Yes, I get your point. Unfortunately, I don't have the exact because I'm just
partnering those who really develop it.
Because I don't have the exact answer about
the speed of the model, the time of the model.
But I remember during the presentation, they explained
They presented that usually they build the model first and they integrate
into the robot. But when they reach to the field now, the robot first
scans the field, and it's not that
long. The time for now analyzing and
classification is within few minutes. It's not that long.
So when it drives into the farm,
it's not long.
Unfortunately, I don't have the exact number because we are just collaborating.
So we are trying to
extend their solution, if I can say like that.
We are collab.
Okay.
One quick one, if
there is one.
If not, let's thank the speaker again.
And from a lot of stuff about images that we've seen so far,
we're moving to sound. So, let's welcome to the stage,
Cong Lin
from the Chinese Academy of Sciences, who is going to tell us about
Soundscapes China.
Thank you. Okay.
Hello, everyone.
I come from China, the Institute of Geology.
And I want to share the topics about Soundscape
China. We
initiate this project
to collect nature sounds by AI.
And my topics includes four parts.
Firstly,
I think
when you see these images, the sounds of the birds, the
mammals, the frogs, and the sounds of the wind,
the rain, the thunders,
are emerging in your brain. And soundscape ecology
takes the sounds within a landscape and its
research
subject, exploring the distribution and variation
patterns across different spatial and temporal
dimensions.
So
we research on the sounds of
animals and also their
living environment.
This image shows the soundscape and the relationship
between biodiversity. And the genetic diversity
is related to
how or what sounds or species
happened. And the species diversity, ecosystem
diversity, and landscape diversity
may result in the components of the soundscape,
the sounds diversity. And
maybe culture diversity is also very close to
the soundscape because many music art
are generated
from the nature sounds.
So,
nature sounds
diversity is an important indicator
of biodiversity. And
the passive acoustic monitoring
has become an important means of biodiversity
monitoring.
And China
wants to build a broad monitoring network
nationwide. So there's some urgent
things we need to do. The first is to
develop and select standard sound sensors.
The sensor is
4 or 5G, and with long
battery life and suitability for various
field work for building the monitoring network.
Second, we need a nature sound database
covering multiple categories, multiple
regions, and long time series for training AI
models for monitoring system.
And we encourage the public to contribute their data
and encourage sound art
creation, thereby enhancing our outreach
capacity.
Why Soundscape China? So we try to provide a
platform for testing sound sensors or sound
devices from different companies
in real-world
scenarios,
and then collecting nature sounds in various habitats
to build a database,
and training models for sound event detection and species
recognition. Also involving the public
and artists in contributing their
creativity on nature sounds.
So this is our framework of Soundscape China.
And how we organize this project.
Okay, this is the framework.
Firstly, we want to create or build a platform
that includes various sensors, sound models,
and sound database. And
we have many parties involved into this project, like
institutes, universities, governments, and public.
And we will provide
multiple services like data sharing,
audio annotation, audio analysis, and model
training.
And also we face to biodiversity monitoring,
sound art, and citizen science. So this is the whole framework
of our project. And
this is the management team. And
I am responsible for the monitoring group.
And
Colin, the other Colin, is responsible for the sound
art group. And
Gao is
responsible for the citizen science group.
And
He and Zhang responsible of field training
work.
And this is the list of our partner
organizations, include some institutions, some
government departments, and some universities.
Yeah. And I want to share some progress on this project.
And firstly, we called for the equipments.
So we have
about
280 devices now, and they have been
deployed in different
places across China.
And
below, this is the devices we had
get from the different companies.
And we have standards.
Firstly, the devices should be 4 or
5G that can automatically transfer the
data back,
and it should be solar-powered,
and
should meet more than 50
days storage. And also we have plugin for
microphone that can be used by the citizen science.
This is the users.
More than about
110 organizations are
participating in this
project, and they get the
devices. They
deploy
these devices. Okay.
Okay, these images, those people get the
devices and then go outside into the fields to
install to
the devices outside. And then the data will
transfer automatically to our platform.
And this is the
network and the sites we have deployed
the
devices and more than 260
sites have been
deployed.
And this is our platform, Soundscape China.
And we also have a citizen science app that people
can record
the sounds around them and
upload the sounds to our platform.
And we also use the DownCall archive for our data
standard, but some
data cannot be included in the DownCall standard,
like equipment. I cannot find the equipment component.
And also we extend and localize the DownCall
to make it better suited to Chinese application.
And we have an annotation tool. So,
we also have volunteers working on this platform so they can
label our audio data.
And this is a model framework, and this is proposed
by our team. And
we try to
pre-train the
data from the two dimension, the time
dimension and the frequency dimension.
And the spectrum is patched
into small square and then pre-trained.
And this pre-trained model can be used in the downstream
task, like sound event detection and classification.
Okay.
And this is the data. We have collected more than
3.6 million
records now, one year. Just only one year.
Okay. And this is some examples we have collected
from different
permits. I don't want to show this.
And
okay.
Okay. This is a video, but I think I have no time to show you.
But this is
some people go outside to make a few
recordings. They are working hard to do
their job. And I
want to share the study case in Shandong Province, and we have
three
monitoring sites, and we have collect
many datas
for
analysis. And we can
see the sound events, the
bird call events
across
every day and
24 hours. And we can see the
peak of the sound event in different sites,
different birds. Okay. And also,
the trends
With different environment factors,
how the environmental factor affect the sound events.
And this program is endorsed by ISSP.
ISSP is in UNESCO
Science Decades.
And next step, we will call for more
devices from different companies for testing,
and then we will build our more broad
network for Soundscape China. And then we will
publish audio datasets to public for
non-commercial use. And yes, we have
annotated many audio
data now that we can release this for research.
And then we continuously refine the acoustic
recognizing model through iterative training,
and then accelerate the field recording training and
promote data science and sound art creation.
Yes, we have many artists about sound involved in
this project.
Okay.
This is the
last slide. And I want to thank all
the people, all the organizations involved into this project.
And thank you. My name is Colin. You can call me Colin.
My Chinese is hard to pronounce. Okay. Thank you, everyone.
Thank you, Colin, for that. So we have time for one or two questions. Go ahead.
Yeah. Thank you very much.
An obvious question to me is, what about extending the frequency range?
Because there are a lot of species that are significant components of the
ecosystem that are above 20 kilohertz, for example,
like bats are the obvious one. But that could easily be true of
things below 20 hertz as well,
say in the African system. Have you thought about expanding, or
are there products out there that handle a higher frequency
range?
I cannot catch. I'll review.
Yeah. I was asking if there was any
idea that you may have to extend the frequency range
to species that are operating, say,
above 20 kilohertz, like bats, and they are
significant
players in the ecosystem.
For-
No?
No.
Sorry.
I'll speak to you afterwards.
Okay.
Do we have any other questions?
Yeah.
Over the
technical things that pop out in my mind, something
I really want to ask is, the first time I approached
the idea of the sounds of a biotope
or ecology piece,
it was through the idea of the extinction of the experience
and the amnesia of the ecological things we're living
of. And
one thing that stayed in my mind in that moment was, what
can we lose by letting
this part of what makes a group of
biodiversity getting loose, the
different ways and dynamics, the sounds works to give an
environment its identity. And now with AI era,
we have the opportunity of use this data in
ways I really want to hear.
You mean use AI
to...
Oh, yes. So my question was more on
what have we lose by letting
some sounds
and their identity as a group in a ecological
unit disappear?
Sorry, I cannot catch what you-- But-
Yes
... we can talk each other.
Yeah. Of course.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thank you, Colin. So our next speaker is Jenna Klein from
MIT, which will be a virtual presentation, so it should be
coming up any time now.
Thank
you. Any time now.
I will just stand here whilst we're waiting.
Okay, there we go.
My name is Jenna Klein, and I'm a post-doc at MIT.
I'll be presenting some of the work I did during my PhD studies
on autonomous systems for ecological monitoring, with a
particular focus on my recent work for cross-modal
coordination for biodiversity monitoring at scale.
As I'm sure all of us are aware, biodiversity is being
lost at an unprecedented rate across the globe.
But this biodiversity that we would like to protect,
understand, and preserve is concentrated in parts of the world that
are hardest to monitor
and areas where we have the least data, as this image shows.
However,
we now have access to numerous data sources that we can
use to start filling in those gaps.
We have satellite images, static sensors like
camera traps and acoustic monitors,
drones, citizen science apps like iNaturalist and
eBird, and GPS sensors for on-animal
recording.
And along with these sensor streams, we also have new powerful
AI models that can analyze these vast volumes of data
at scale.
So what this workflow has looked like for the past decade or so is,
first, an ecologist or team goes out and collects the data.
The data is stored and then analyzed using AI.
This approach treats sensing, inference, and analysis as separate
stages,
which is quite useful for analyzing vast volumes of data,
but there is no room to adjust the sensing
strategy in real time, and can also lead
to delayed insights with the lead
time between data collection and analysis.
So how can we begin to use these tools to
better evaluate conservation policies at biologically
meaningful scales?
Currently, it's very challenging for stakeholders to evaluate whether their
conservation policies are working at the scales where
change unfolds.
Macro-scale satellite monitoring can track landscape
changes,
but not behavior,
and small-scale sensors like camera traps and manual sampling
can
gather very fine-grained
data over small areas, but are challenging to scale.
Ecological monitoring is increasingly requiring autonomous
systems that can make decisions in the field
at the far edge. So what do I mean when I say far edge?
There are two main meanings. One is the physical far edge,
remote field sites where deployments happen, and the
computational far edge,
on commodity edge hardware with
strict latency budgets and intermittent connectivity.
And this approach treats both the physical far
edge and the computational far edge as the same design problem.
So to start to tackle this, one of the contributions of my thesis
was to reframe ecological sensing as an adaptive
edge systems problem,
using AI-driven animal ecology
to close the sensing loop to enable adaptive
sampling.
I first focused
on single modality smart sensors, namely building
autonomous drone systems to track animal herds in real
time.
So the first iteration involved autonomous
tracking,
redefining the object of interest as the herd, which increased the
yield of useful data for downstream tasks.
The second addition added behavior adaptive
flight as a safety feature
to assist the pilot in monitoring for signs of disturbance
and adjusting in real time.
And then finally, a surface of interest aware,
which enabled pilots to configure the system
to capture the exact data needed for a particular research question and
species, whether it be tracking, behavior, or even individual
ID.
For example, elephants could be individually identified by their ears,
while zebras and giraffes require a flank view, as seen
here. So with that knowledge, the drone can adjust its
path depending on which
data needs to be collected.
So this approach showed that AI-driven animal
ecology
is feasible in the field. This has been tested in both
Ohio and Kenya, and also shows that
AI in the loop can increase the yield of usable data.
But drones aren't the only sensors available to
us. For some of my thesis work, I was particularly
interested in drones since they offer a high level of
behavioral detail. But other sensors, as shown
in this figure, offer much better temporal and
spatial coverage.
So if we consider drones
as the mobile aerial node of a multimodal sensing
system,
how can we design these systems so
drones can complement static and ground-based modalities?
If we want to monitor ecosystems at scale,
this really requires a cross-modal coordination,
since different modalities capture complementary
ecological and behavioral signals at different costs.
So I propose leveraging sensors' complementary strengths to
design better systems.
But how can we
start to think about provisioning these systems?
How much compute is required?
How much energy? Is solar sufficient?
What type of infrastructure is needed?
What sensors make sense to deploy?
So to start answering those questions,
we conducted a summer-long field campaign at The
Wilds, which is North America's largest safari park,
located in Eastern Ohio and managed by the Columbus Zoo.
It's a former strip mine, now a conservation and
restoration research site.
Our study focused on a 200-acre pasture,
which is home to milu deer, takin, and
Przewalski horses
with a known census ground truth. So we knew exactly how many
animals to expect and could
measure the different sensors' relative accuracy
in recovering those census counts fairly.
And at the end of the summer, we ended up with
almost 400,000 occurrences across
five modalities. And a key contribution here
was the metadata, which allowed us to
cross-reference these different modalities
both temporally and spatially.
So with this dataset,
we can now begin to ask questions about unlocking new
capabilities to coordinate across sensors.
So, an alarm on a camera trap can trigger a
drone, for example. An interesting acoustic event
can cause our camera trap network to turn on.
A citizen science observation could trigger
other modalities to investigate a unique event that
may not be detected otherwise.
So using the Smart Wilds dataset,
I came up with a method to use
synchronized traces to understand these
coupled provisioning decisions before expensive field
trials.
The choice of model, hardware, the sensor
configuration, and the data filter threshold
all impact what the overall workload is on
the system.
Previously, it would've been impossible to
begin to understand how these systems
are configured before expensive field trials, but these
synchronized multimodal datasets can now give us a tool to understand
these.
However, these biodiversity datasets must be usable
for both the robotics and AI research communities
to support this development of cross-modal coordination system
developments.
So in summary, cross-modal coordination can
assist in scaling data collection,
enable real-time adaptivity,
support non-invasive monitoring, and advance
better-informed conservation policies.
Thank you so much for your time and attention.
If you would like to discuss any of the topics I've mentioned today,
please feel free to contact me. Thank you.
Hello, everyone, and thank you for the opportunity to present today.
My name is Jenna Klein, and I'm a post-doc at MIT.
Okay. I don't think it's possible to ask questions for now.
There is a Q&A and a chat function in Whova, so
if you want to ask questions online, it's possible.
But in the meantime, we can continue with our next speaker,
and learn a bit about camera trapping and AI.
So please welcome to the stage, Karolina.
Yeah, there's an on button.
God. Why am I talking so loud?
No?
Hello? Okay, got it. Thank you.
All right. Hello, everyone. I am Karolina Kuczkowska.
I'm a data manager at the Polish Node of GBIF, and I work at Open Science
Conservation Fund. It's an NGO started at the Mammal
Research Institute of the Polish Academy of Sciences in
Bialowieza, and that is where we develop Trapper, open-source
software for managing camera trapping projects.
And that's what I would like to tell you about today.
A little bit of a background, although maybe it's not that needed at this point.
Camera trapping has been steadily gaining popularity over many years now,
and this is due to several reasons.
Hardware is becoming cheaper and more accessible.
There are more methods developed for monitoring and researching animals using
camera traps as well as specifically in the last couple of years,
a couple of very cool AI models have been released to streamline this
work as well.
Camera trapping generates very big datasets,
and those cool models are around, but still, many institutions rely on manual
analysis of this data. And manual analysis means that it can
take a year or longer between when the picture is taken and when the
researchers find out what is in this picture.
So this branch of research really needs automation.
So how does Trapper fit into this picture?
Trapper is an open-source data infrastructure for managing data in camera
trapping projects. And when I say data infrastructure, I mean it's not
just a single app that you put your photos into and get some kind of AI results.
It's a whole suite of tools for different aspects of managing
these projects for different users with different skills and needs.
Trapper works with videos as well as photos.
This year, Trapper is turning 10, and for most of this time it only worked with
photos.
But we are now working on a big update.
That's what Trapper version two is, and it's capable of analyzing
videos as well. It is still in the final testing phase, but we're planning an
official release before the end of this year.
Trapper enables both AI and human annotation.
So on the one hand, it gives you the benefit of automation, but on the other hand,
you still have human in the loop. You still have expert supervision on these
results.
Trapper can use many different AI models in a fully customizable pipeline.
It's scalable, it's suitable for running projects of different sizes, small up
to big and very big as well.
And Trapper is compatible with Camtrap DP data standard.
So let's now zoom in on a couple of these qualities.
As I said, the entire project is open source. So this QR code.
My point? Yeah. So this QR code will take you to our GitLab, and
it's half of the repositories that we have in there.
So there are different tools. There are AI processing components,
there is back end, there is graphical interface that is easy and intuitive
for users who use that. But there are also command line tools for users who are a
little bit more experts and who want to do some automation of those processes.
And that's what it looks like.
So,
this is a video that has been passed through this AI pipeline, and you can see
that there are bounding boxes around animals. They have all had assigned species.
Those are European bison from the Bialowieza forest, and you can see approximations
of the skeletons as well. And when you click on one of these bounding boxes on the
right-hand side, a form appears, and that's when an expert can
either correct or input any information that they want to.
So that's the Trapper
version two interface.
And this AI pipeline contains several different
steps, and for each of these steps, you can choose out of available models.
So first steps, of course, is object detection.
That's the part that tells you this picture contains animal, human,
vehicle, or there's nothing in this picture. That's the first phase.
And for this, we mostly use MegaDetector, but other YOLO-based models are
available as well.
The next stage is taking the bounding boxes that were detected as
animals and sending them to a model that detects the species.
And the selection of this model depends on where you are and what species you want
to research. There is a whole suite of models available.
And for pictures, that's the pipeline.
For videos, however, it gets a little bit more complicated.
So imagine you have an animal detected in one frame of the video and then animal
detected in another frame of a video.
To get accurate counts, it's important to know if it's the same animal or two
different ones. So that's where tracking algorithms come in.
There are several available trackers to use.
As well, we also employ custom post-processing to make this tracking even more
accurate.
There is pose tracking algorithm.
That's what gives you those skeleton estimations that you've seen in the video.
For now, we only use pose tracking to improve the tracking accuracy, but
also
in the future, we would like to use it to add models to determine animal behavior,
because with the skeleton, it's not that difficult at this point.
And another thing that we are working on right now is...
Maybe I'll just jump to code if you're taking pictures.
So depth estimation, that's the models that tell you how far the animal is from the
camera,
and this information can be used in different models that estimate
population sizes. And this QR code here, this will take you to our documentation.
It contains lots of different information, but specifically explains details
about this AI pipeline and gives you some details about all of these available
models. Trapper is designed so that it's easy to incorporate
new models. So if there's a model in architecture similar to
these that we already have implemented, all you need to do is fill out a simple
form, upload your model weight, and then it can work in Trapper.
And if it's an architecture that is not yet implemented, all you have to do is
write a simple Python connector class,
map models data to Trapper internal data, and then you
can plug in new models as well. So as soon as new open source models pop up, we can
have them in Trapper.
As I told you, Trapper is scalable, so depending on the resources you have and on
the amount of media that you have to process, you can deploy Trapper on different
platforms.
If neither internet nor electricity are an issue, you
can use powerful cloud servers or bare metal servers to deploy Trapper.
In the environments where internet access may not be that
reliable, you can use local machines to deploy Trapper as
well. So it's either a personal computer or hardware like Nvidia Spark.
And in the environments where both internet and
electricity can be not that reliable, the entire Trapper stack,
and that includes the AI processing components as well, can be deployed on
microservers like Nvidia Jetson or
Raspberry Pi.
And that's the technical side of the scalability.
Basically, the entire Trapper stack runs wherever Docker is available.
We
can use different processor architectures, and for the AI acceleration,
you can do it on CPU alone, you can do it on GPU, and for edge
devices, it also works on Halo processors.
And most of this ability to run Trapper on
microservers was achieved thanks to Trapper Keeper project.
It was financed by Wild Labs. We just finished it a couple of months ago.
In 2025, the project was given Wild Labs award.
So Trapper Keeper is this little piece of hardware here.
Basically, it's a Raspberry Pi or another microserver put into this small
box that protects it from the elements.
And this is something that you can take into the field.
So you can just take this box, go directly to your camera trap, take the SD
card, plug it in.
... add a screen as well. It's not that interesting without a screen.
But if you plug in a screen, then you can just watch Trapper working live on this
tiny machine here. Fantastic.
So this work that we have done to enable this computation on the edge
is important for several reasons.
First of all, global biodiversity hotspots are typically areas
with difficult access to infrastructure, like electricity
or the internet. So enabling using these new technologies on
tiny machines like this lets us take this research where it's
needed. Another thing is that local computation, edge
computation, is a good way to ensure data
privacy and data security, and maybe most importantly,
in a world with a rapidly changing climate, we cannot really ignore
the ecological impacts of large data center.
So we believe that edge computation is the future of responsible
AI use.
Hence, devices like that.
As I said, Trapper is compatible with Camtrap TP data standard.
This QR code will take you to the Camtrap TP standard website.
If you're not yet familiar with the standard, I encourage you to have a look.
So you can export your
research results from Trapper in Camtrap TP data standard, which
enables sharing it with different scientists, as well as publication to
open repositories like GBIF.
So right now, to publish Trapper data into GBIF, you can export
and download your data page and then go to IPT.
And with no extra post-processing required, you can just upload it to IPT and then
it goes to GBIF. However, before the end of this year, I would also like to
implement direct publication to GBIF, so that you don't even have to
download your data at all, just there will be a simple form in Trapper, and then
data goes straight to GBIF. So look out for that.
There are several institutions using Trapper as well.
As I told you, the entire stack is open source, so we don't really know everyone
who is using it. People can just go to GitLab, download it, and run their own
instances. But those are the institutions that we work closely
with.
And this number, over 40 million images, it's a couple of months old, and it's
growing rapidly. So I'm fairly sure it's a little more at this point.
We have a Slack channel. If you are interested in either
developments in Trapper or in general camera trap research, we
have a community of almost 200 experts on the subject that
are there on the Slack, and we would love to have you as well. Thank you.
Thank you. So we have time for a couple of questions.
So does anyone have any questions for Karolina?
Okay.
Who put their hand up first? Okay.
Hi. Thanks. Very interesting talk.
So we use Trap Tagger
for a lot of our camera trap images.
I was just interested in your product, if there's multi-species in a
bounding box, how does it get handled?
Bounding boxes can be overlapping, so that
depends on which model you use. You would need a model specific
to your fauna.
You can have several bounding boxes at the same location.
So that would have to be tested, of course.
I don't know how much examples we have working with that,
but you can have several bounding boxes with different animals that can be assigned
to different labels. So that should work as well.
Perfect. Thank you.
Thank you.
All right.
Yeah.
I was curious about this edge computing and when you run it
on the Jetson in the field, right?
Yeah.
Did you manage to get a sustainable setup where you would have
solar or something and the power supply?
How much it eats? How much
power?
It doesn't need all that much. It can be run entirely on solar.
So there's a way to just attach a small solar panel to this microserver, and then
that's enough power for it. When you have power, when you have electricity,
we can just plug it in, but also a small solar panel is enough to
run this
entire server.
That also comes back to the-
Yep.
If you have the solar,
and you run it locally,
can it run through the night as well?
Are you
using the
camera that has night sight and uses the...
So with solar, you can't run overnight directly.
So how much power do you need to store for the night to run
it 24/7?
That's actually a good question. I don't have good numbers on you.
There's a report for this project, so I can find out for you, but
I don't really have. Also, the idea is you can take it into the field.
You don't necessarily have to. It doesn't have to stay in the field all day.
If you have an access to building with electricity, you can take it in there as
well. It's just possible to take it into the field.
Does anyone have...? Oh, yeah.
Great.
Yeah. Great talk. Have you looked at incorporating individual instance
pattern recognition tools like the Mu
platform that Wellbook generated?
Yeah. We have. That would be one of the planned next steps to extend
this AI pipeline, because right now there are five stages possible.
But there are many ways that this pipeline can be extended.
I mentioned that we're looking into incorporating behavior models, which is not
going to be that difficult once we have the skeleton, but also individual
recognition is another thing that we could do.
If somebody is interested in partnering up for a project that could fund this work,
we are very interested. So
Yes, we have looked into that. There are models for different animals popping up,
as I'm sure you know. In Poland, we do some research on lynx, and there are
interesting models for that as well.
So that would be the next step to extend this AI pipeline. Yes.
Okay, we've got a couple more questions.
Brilliant.
Sorry. Yeah. Talk.
There we go.
Hi. Yes, thank for the presentation. I just have a quick question.
Have you tried or does the platform work
on small species like insect and those thing?
Are you trying that?
Well,
the platform itself is really agnostic of the models. You can run different models.
You
would need a proper camera trap to
see the insects and proper models to recognize them.
Trapper can work with any kind of data from camera traps.
We are not currently using it for any insect products, but it would be possible
because it doesn't really matter from Trapper's perspective what camera trap you
use. You just need pictures from a camera trap, and then once we
incorporate models for insects, it would work as well.
So it would be possible. It's not really on Trapper's side.
If you connect different hardware and different models, it will be possible,
yes.
Great talk. Superb work. I'm interested, are you
planning to extend
sound identifications because video is also recorded
sounds and any plans on that?
Yes, and also there are many
more appearing multimodal datasets with that as well.
So that's another direction that we would like to take Trapper into if we manage to
find the resources for that. What I didn't mention is that Open Science
Conservation Fund is a really small team.
There's four or five of us, depending on the time, and we're working on this
entire thing. So we would really like to take Trapper in many different directions,
but we are actively looking for resources to do that.
But bioacoustic analysis is a very good next direction for us for
several reasons.
There is really no software for managing bioacoustic project.
You can analyze your data. There is good software for that, but for taking care of
all the locations, actually managing these projects, there is not really many good
software. So Trapper would be a very good candidate for that because we already
have the infrastructure. All it would take is to incorporate audio models
and then maybe enable some views with spectrograms or something like that.
That's something we would like to do.
And another thing is that Camtrap-TP model is being developed, is
being extended to accommodate bioacoustic data as well.
I have a talk on this on Thursday, if you're interested.
So Trapper would be a very good candidate to do this data as well.
We would like to do that, yes.
Hello. We can probably do one more question if anyone else has any
questions.
There's one.
Yes. Okay. Coming.
Hello. Can you maybe expand a bit more about the depth
estimation and what applications you are
wanting to use that for?
So that's a project that we're doing with a Polish company right now.
The idea is that there are these methods that enable
estimating population sizes based on how far
the animal appears from the camera.
I don't have a video here, but the way this works is that basically,
first you have to do some calibration.
So you'll place your camera trap, you have a couple of
objects with known distance, and you run the calibration.
And after that is done, every video from this camera trap can be converted into
a heat map of distances, basically.
So at every frame, you can tell how far an animal is from the camera, and this
information can be used for several purposes, the main being
estimation population sizes. There are papers that describe this
particular workflow, how to estimate population size from
the distances of observations. So that's what it's for.
Okay. Thank you.
I'm sure some future uses will pop up as well once it's ready.
Awesome. Okay. Let's thank Karolina one more time.
Thank you.
So just to say, there's also a poll on the
Whova app or Whova desktop by Jenna Klein.
So if you go on to the schedule and then click on
Jenna's talk from today, and then there's a section that
says Poll, and the question is, are you collecting or using
biodiversity data from multiple sensor modalities?
So if you're there, please do fill in Jenna's poll.
Okay, so one more thing before we go.
So we've finished a little bit early, so well done, everyone.
Let's give all of our speakers one more round of applause.
So I think our plan is to go for an early coffee.
But before all of you go, can we just ask all speakers to come to the floor?
Because we're going to do a group photo, apparently.
So speakers and probably the session organizers as well, can you guys come to
the stage so we can do a group photo?
And everyone else, we'll see you in the next session, hopefully.
So this session will continue after the break as well. Okay.
I
think it was moderators.
Oh, moderators.
I would say 11:00 is the...
Oh, should I say, when is the next session?
11:00. It starts back in this room again.
Oh, back in this room at 11:00 for the next session, by the way, guys.
Wait, one more.
And can the speakers come 10 minutes before the start of the session that
we can just make sure that everything is working fine?
And sit near the front, ideally. Okay. Thank you.
It's
from a little video we have.
You can start.
Okay.
Hello, everybody. Welcome.
Sorry that I'm running late. It seems to be a common theme for me.
Okay, so this is the second AI session that we
have today, which is super exciting, and I did run here, so I'm a little out
of breath.
But our first speaker will be...
One second.
Okay.
So welcome back. Once again, I'm Kit, and I'd like to thank all of these lovely
organizers. And this is our second session, and our first
speaker of today will be
about assessing the readiness of plant image datasets for AI-enabled
spatially explicit ecological monitoring. That sounds super cool.
A systematic review of bias, representativeness,
and annotation quality. So please welcome
to the stage Yucun Zhao, and
take it away.
Can you hear me?
Oh.
You can also have this one. It's not working.
This one. Hi.
Still not working?
Is it working? Okay, it's working now. Hi, everyone.
My name's Yucun. I changed my topic to a slightly easier one
for you to understand it.
And yeah, so the topic is Are Plant Image
Datasets Ready for AI-Embedded Community
Assessment? The content will be the same as what you
read on
the description there. And
I'm from the School of Natural and Environmental Sciences of Newcastle University.
And let's start.
So I think this might be a bit too easy for
you here, but... Oh, sorry.
Hello.
Okay.
Okay. I'll continue. Okay.
But today, AI is everywhere in our life, and we are asking
different questions to the AI, to
ask it for different questions, different answers.
And here we have three main different types
of the
imaging tasks. So firstly is the classification tasks,
which aim to answer the present or not question.
For example, here we have this image, and we can ask whether there's a buttercup.
It said, yes, there is a buttercup, and there's no oxalis,
there's no plantain. And then we come to object detection tasks,
where we can ask the question of
where is the flower of the buttercup, and it can provide us a
boundary box
saying that, oh, it is here. And then thirdly is the
segmentation tasks.
It will ask where it is, but on top of that, it will ask where
exactly it is and what is the cover percentage of each species.
So all these kind of tasks can
potentially enhance efficiency, reduce labor intensity, expand
spatial coverage, and they are easier to standardization as well.
However, if we think about how AI works, it's not like magic.
It's not like we just give it our image and ask the question, it
can give us the answer. It's not working like that.
We have to put datasets there,
select
a proper model, and use our data to train the model.
So finally, the performance of the model depends on the model
structure and the availability and quality of the training data.
And today, I'm going to focus on the latter one, which is the dataset
quality.
So as we can identify there, there is a very rapid
advances in AI models, which the
computing scientists worked really hard on that.
However, from ecological perspective, there are not
enough ecological image datasets.
There is still a large gap between that, which forces us to answer the question
of are existing ecological image datasets
fit for the question we increasingly expect
AI to address?
In order to answer that question systematically, we developed
a framework which is inspired by the clinical
framework and the FAIR principles.
So we developed this framework for reporting and for assessing the
readiness of the ecological image datasets, and this is
specially targeting on vegetation images.
But
I think we can adjust it for a broader
application by just twisting a little bit of it.
So
we propose four different dimensions, where the first one is
training relevant dataset characteristics, which including
the characters we need to train the model, including
image number, image resolution, class number and definition,
instance number, and class distribution.
And the second dimension is about image acquisition
characteristics, which include a lot.
So it's like plant growth stages, year and growing seasons,
viewing angles and plant orientations, geographic locations and
habitats, reproducible image acquisition protocol,
and environmental and weather conditions.
The third dimension is the annotation protocol, which is very important
for us as the ecologist.
So
it includes detailed and reproducible annotation protocol,
annotation quality control method, and annotation consistency
assessment. And finally is the dataset accessibility,
which include public availability.
And after
building this framework, we carried out a systematic review to apply this framework
on and to
adjust the framework based on our result of the systematic review.
So here we choose the topic of RealField, which is in situ plant
object detection and segmentation tasks which target on
non-crop vegetations. So-
We choose this topic because currently all of us know that we can just
use our phone, click it, and the Google will tell us what plant species is there.
But this kind of classification dataset can only
answer the question of what is it.
There are very
large scale and well-established classification
datasets, which all of us can easily
access. However, we tend to ask the AI
more complex questions, including where is it and what area
does it occupy. So these kind of questions need
spatially explicit tasks, including object detection and
segmentation datasets, and those are quite limited.
Our
review focused on the following three questions: What datasets are
currently available? What applications do they target on?
And what methodological challenges exist regarding
this set quality, ecological validity, and bias?
So this is our result.
After applying our searching strategy, we have a total of 508
studies, where 360 were
unique studies were screened.
And finally, we got the result of only 40 datasets which
are eligible.
So first, let's have a look of the very basic
informations, where there is an increasing trend, especially
for the black color, which is the object detection
tasks.
But for other tasks, for example, segmentation
tasks, is not increasing as much.
And
for the dataset acquisition modes,
ground level and UAV imagery is still dominant.
Where we find out is the increasing use of
customer-grade devices like, for example,
smartphones and
the small drones.
And dataset size is very uneven in number
of images and instance.
Then there is a very uneven geographic distribution,
where most
datasets are from Europe and Asia, where most of the
ecological hotspots were neglected.
And even though we did not include any crop-related
tasks, the agriculture applications still dominant,
which most of them focus on wheat.
About the target bias, we can see there are 19 out of
40 focusing on wheat detection or segmentation, followed
by tree crown
segmentation or detection, which we have eight.
And there are three for wildflowers, where there are very limited
focusing on other applications. For example, I put
two there, where the top one is the whole plant segmentation from a
rainforest, and the second one is a pasture
segmentation.
So as we can see there, there is still a bias
there where we tend to prioritize
predefined target species or even organs
with the annotation regions, which are the boxes or the color you can
see there. However, there are other plants which is
on the background, and those plants are always neglected.
Finally, we come to the dataset quality, which we
applied our framework to carry out a
very
basic analysis
according the image acquisition characteristic and the annotation
protocol. So overall, the quality of the plant image datasets
still need to be improved, and especially for
the annotation protocol is not very satisfied.
So we think
it's very
important to build reproducible annotation protocols.
So finally, let's come back to the question we asked
from the very beginning.
Our answer to the question is current datasets
are still not fully ready for AI-embedded ecological monitoring.
So what kind of datasets we need in the future is still based on the four
dimensions we proposed earlier. So we need sufficient and
representative datasets with reproducible and
contextual image acquisition methods,
and we need consistent and quality-controlled annotation
protocol. And finally, they should be public available.
And that's it. Thank you.
Cool. So we actually have
time for a couple of questions, and I'm coming to the back.
Oh, and great talk.
Thank you.
Here you go.
Hi. Thanks. Nice talk. I'm wondering how
realistic it is that ecological data will ever achieve the
quality
we, as modelers, ideally would need to have,
basically. And so my question to you is,
is there a middle ground, or should we not work more on architectures
that are better able actually to work with the crappy data we often have
as ecologists?
Do you mean the architecture of the models?
Yeah.
Yes. Right. I think so basically my idea is the
datasets
provide us the basic to train the models.
So even though we have very good models, we still need good quality of data.
So that's the idea. But of course, with the same quality of data,
as you mentioned, it's not very realistic to
fulfill all the requirements. So if
in the case we cannot fulfill the requirements, better model structure will
definitely help a lot.
Okay. Oh, that is all the time we have for questions, and
thank you again for your talk. So our next one
will be the WildLiVE Portal: Towards Scalable
Wildlife Monitoring through the Integration of
Citizen Science and Human-in-the-Loop AI Workflows.
And that will be given by Rajaprithi Rajendran, and if you'd
like to come up. Thank you.
Yes.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Rajaprithi, working in Senckenberg Frankfurt, and today I will be
talking about the WildLiVE Portal, the platform which we are building for
wildlife monitoring. And in this talk specifically, I will focus
for how we have integrated citizen scientists in the human-in-the-loop
in the AI workflows.
Moving on to the motivation, why are we building it?
As many of you know, there are three key challenges in
wildlife monitoring. The first is the data, and the next is the storage, and
the third is the scale of the data. So often, camera
traps are set in the field, and the images are
captured and stored in the local drive.
And this image often requires annotation and verification,
and here we are talking about millions of images which needs to be
annotated and verified. So our idea is to facilitate the
complete lifecycle management of wildlife monitoring.
When the data is collected, we would like to offer a platform
which we can manage it,
identify with the help of AI, and brings in human-in-the-loop
and analyze and further publish the data in the fair manner.
So in the nutshell, the platform offers the data management,
and it allows for the AI workflows to create
an automated annotation and bring citizen scientists and experts
as a human in the loop. And further, we will be offering the
VRE, Virtual Research Environment, to further analyze the outcome of the project
and publish the data in the fair manner.
At the right side, what you see is the landing page of the
platform which we are developing,
which still we are building and trying to enhance at the moment.
And here you can see two option to explore
the projects and the camera station and the images captured from the
camera stations. And I will go one by one of this component
and speak more about the human-in-the-loop workflow.
So how we are doing the data management, the platform currently supports
a CamtrapDB import,
and also we can set up the camera stations and the
capture events manually at the platform.
And we also have our own ontology, which we call as Wildlife Monitoring
Ontology. This is built on the standards such as
SOSA and OA. And when the data comes in, we
map it to our ontology and create a station setup and capture event.
And once the AI or manual identification is done, then it
will add some annotation. At the end, the data will be exported as a
CamtrapDB format.
Moving further to the AI workflows.
We call it as a multimodal object detection.
That is, we are not specifically depends on one single detector.
We have a model registry where the models can be maintained and versioned.
At the right side, which you see is our API of a model registry and the
example of how we
register the models. And at the moment, we have SpeciesNet and also
one of the model which we have trained for the specific
project to detect jaguars from Bolivia and South
Africa. And
this doesn't stop here. We are moving towards the
infrastructure where we can also host our partners' model into our
platform, and also we can schedule the mass models which are
hosted on the external infrastructure.
This way we say, bring your own model, not only your dataset.
If you want to bring your model and try to host it in our platform, we support it.
And how this is done, basically when the image comes in and the
model registry will check for which images needs to pass in.
If it's a internally hosted model, then it passes to
that model, and if it's external infrastructure, then it
will call the API and gets a result back.
Here you can see the classification back from the AI model.
And now we have different models and have a different class
names. We need a stable identifier,
common for all the models. So we have integrated Catalog of Life.
When the model runs, then
it passes a scientific name to the Checklist Bank API and get back the
scientific name, vernacular name and the species identifier.
So here what you see in the UI, we also offers the
species picker. Here you can type either common name or the scientific name,
and we will get back the species identifier.
And
now comes a very hard question. Can this annotation be trusted?
Can this be counted directly as a scientific evidence?
So that's when the human-in-the-loop comes in the picture.
We have introduced two more terms to our ontology, which is
classification and verification, to differentiate which mission have created
it or who have involved in the approval process of this
annotation. And also we maintain the provenance history of
this. At the right side, what you see is the verification workflow, where
the
Model have classified it, and we have the classification status as mission,
and we have a verification pending at the moment.
And then the citizen scientist or the domain experts comes in and
approve it. And also you can see the history of which model created it and
who the user approved it.
And
then again comes the question, can all of these annotations,
can a human verify it manually? So we have
introduced consensus where at the project level or at the individual capture
event level, you can say, okay, if you're confident about this model's
performance is good at 95%, then you can set the confidence
threshold, and all those annotations will be automatically
approved. And the remaining annotations can domain experts or the citizen
scientists can come in and approve it.
And this is about the verification.
We preserve the original annotation created by the machine
and all the verification workflows on top of those
annotations. So we have one annotation and one provenance object,
and all the verification workflow are appended to that object.
And until now, we have seen about how the data comes into the
portal and how the A workflows runs and the human involved
in the
verification. Then for the further analysis, we have a
virtual research environment powered by GeoEngine,
where we have an access to various earth observation datasets that
Sentinel-2, Copernicus land cover, and burn dataset, and much more.
Here at the right side, you see the GIFs and some of the plots
plotted for species distribution and also the features over time.
And
at the end, we wanted to publish the data in a fair manner, which
we call WebEFA digital object with RO-Crate and FAIR
signposting, where to make the data machine actionable.
At the right side, what you see is the human-readable view,
and the center view says, machine actionable RO-Crate data,
where a machine can harvest
from this. And at the right side, which you see is the FAIR signposting,
which have the metadata of this object, where you get information
about how to license it and how to cite it.
And as an outlook and what our future steps on
the AI side,
our project stakeholders are working on active learning to
prioritize which annotation needs to be
reviewed at first. And also, right now we have a SpeciesNet
model in the platform, which
already incorporates MeHA detector.
So we wanted to separate it and flag the human or vehicle
or the
image or some
blank images, which we don't need in the platform.
And also, we are moving towards AI readiness with GeoCrossScience,
combining in-situ measurements with observed earth observation data.
And at the moment, the platform
has a way to say this is a sensitive location and blur the
coordinates, but we wanted to automate this pipeline by bringing in
IUCN Red List checks, so we know this is a sensitive species, and this
location will be automatically blurred.
And at the end goal, we wanted to mobilize directly data
into the GBIF. So we are working towards all of
this.
And
thank you. And this is the wildlife portal from raw data
to FAIR publishable data by bringing in human and
AI
workflows together. And this is my contact, and this is a QR code of a
portal. Please feel free to explore it. Thank you.
Thank you.
Awesome. Do we have any questions?
Okay. Short walk this time.
Just a very basic question. So, you're also using AI for
the reviewing and detecting the blank images and the people, and I
was just wondering, so by blank images, do you mean where no detections have been
found, or detections have been found with a very low threshold?
Oh, could you repeat it, sorry.
So can you just explain a little bit the part where you're using AI
to detect the blank images and the people?
As a MeHA detector, there is a class to say whether it's
animal or human or it's a blank image.
So right now, we have a SpeciesNet, and already you can split
it into the SpeciesNet and the MeHA detector on top of it.
So just that we need a workflow to pass all the images at the import
and pass it to the MeHA detector and flag it and tell the users that
there are
images with human or the blank images, and would you like to
remove it? And it will be removed.
And is that working well? I just ask because we've done a similar thing
where we've had instances where things were detected as
an insect, and it was actually a human, so completely wrong.
So I was wondering how you were getting on with that.
I get the point. That's why we wanted to tell the data uploaders
to review it and saying that we are not responsible for this data,
and we will remove it. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you so much.
No problem.
I actually have a question, but does anybody else have one before I go?
Cool. So I saw that you were using some earth observations with
satellites. Are you incorporating any high-resolution,
airborne airplane observations for these?
Right now,
this dataset is provided by our partner, GeoEngine.
They're trying to bring in more earth observation dataset
into the platform. So that's how we are trying to map it. Yeah.
Okay, perfect. Thank you.
Yeah.
We have time for one more question, if anybody has one.
I can wait.
Okay. Well,
thank you so much. Lovely talk, and we'll get moving on to our
next one.
Oops.
Sorry.
You're good.
So our next talk is going to be HerbAudit, and that is
going to be about validating AI-driven herbarium transcriptions.
And welcome our speaker to the stage.
Do you hear me? Yes. Perfect. Hello, everyone.
I'm Dilara from Ghent University.
But before I start, I would like to thank you, all TADWIG members, for giving
this opportunity to present my work.
And today, I will introduce to you a tool called HerbAudit that
can help us to evaluate our herbarium transcription results produced
by AI.
But first of all, as many of you know, manual herbarium transcription can be
slow, costly, and labor-intensive.
At New York's Botanical Garden alone, average rate of
databasing complete records is 10 specimen per hour.
For 1.3 million specimen, that meant
130,000 staff hours.
AI definitely can offer speed here, but can we really
trust it fully? That's where we realized that there is no
clear benchmark available in the community to evaluate our results
directly.
And incomplete or inaccurate GBIF records also limits their
use as a ground truth. Here's a concrete example.
If you look at the label of this herbarium sheet, we see that the author name and
year information, A.G. Clark, 1857.
If we compare with GBIF records, we see that there is a mistake on the initial, and
there is no date information at all.
This is exactly kind of error that goes invisible
unless someone goes and checks the primary source.
So let's dive into the tool itself.
We can divide HerbAudit into two parts.
The first part is the transcription.
In here, each field extracted in a single AI call and
mapped directly into a structured Darwin Core records.
We will come back into evaluation parts later, but first, let's
go and look at how HerbAudit handles the transcription part.
First of all,
it detects the labels and make the collage via Leaf Machine.
It's also used in Watervision. But unlike Watervision,
HerbAudit does not use a separate OCR step.
Everything happens in a single model call.
That reduces the time and also the cost.
And later, HerbAudit maps all the
extracted field in a Darwin Core format.
And
depends on the user input, it can give
transcription or evaluation report, and as well as an Excel file.
So here is an example. And transcription
part is also logs on its own metadata, like the resolution
information, which model it used, the token information, and the
corresponding cost.
So let's come back into evaluation parts.
As we know, in biodiversity, two different things can mean the same things, like
synonyms in taxonomy. So we have to be careful that we
do not penalize AI wrongly.
So we have to come up with a different logic for each field.
But before going into that, I also
would like to talk about the dataset we manually created.
It's 90 specimen from 63 different institutions
worldwide. It has a lot of variety.
We also categorized them into handwritten, typed, and mixed sheets, based
on their labels. And after that, we
manually annotated those 90 herbarium sheets, several
people,
and via Label Studio. Okay. Let's come back
into how we evaluate the fields.
First one is the taxonomy one. If HerbAudit detects a full
match, it gives a full credit. But if HerbAudit detects a mismatch, it
goes first to role frontline, and after GBIF specimen, it looks
for a relationship. As I said, we do not want to penalize AI wrongly.
And if there's no relationship found, it simply falls back to
their error rates, and it just look at how different the two strings are.
For collector name, HerbAudit first split into words and
then match by character error rate.
It's order-independent, given that collector name can have a lot of
varieties.
For event date, of course, we cannot use character error rate here.
We look at how close the two dates actually are.
For example, is it different by one date or
one month or one year? Then we handle it explicitly.
For geography, we use iso tree normalization, meaning that
United States of America, it will all goes to
the one simple code, USA.
And also, we implemented transliteration, meaning that other
alphabets will transliterate to Latin alphabets.
And here, we use word-based locality matching, ignoring order and punctuation,
given that locality text can be quite detailed.
So lastly, the coordinates here.
It's scored by real-world distance using Haversine
module.
If HerbAudit
detects no coordinate information, it fall back to
geocode and geocode's locality text as a fallback.
So this is how it looks like. It's an interactive HTML report.
User can have an ID,
like the accuracy by fields and the mean accuracy, and
also
how each field is scored. This is all given
in the interactive HTML report.
And user also can have a detailed information for each
specimen and how it's scored.
If the herbarium sheets are already on GBIF, you can directly use it, the
evolution part.
And it will compare the two, and it will give you a score.
But of course, if it's a synonym or doubtful taxonomy, it will exclude
from the score, and it will flag to the user where did it find
and an explanation as well.
So after, of course, we
developed this tool, we wondered which AI model gives the best value.
And if we look at this plot, we can definitely see that
Gemini outperform OpenAI here.
And the best
model sits right on the frontier line, Gemini 3.5 Lite.
And surprisingly,
the local models here, Gemma, are closing the gap between those
paid API models with the 90% at zero
cost.
Of course, we later benchmarked Herbot against pretty well-known
transcription tools like Haspy and Roger Vision.
Since they do not have a common model, we had to compare with
their own backbones. And we see that Herbot wins both
comparisons with the full extraction coverage.
Herbot did not fail any herbarium sheets.
And in here we see that
it summarizes the Herbot accuracy distribution
by the label category. And we see that the typed sheets
in orange
score best with the tightest box. The mixed sheets come
second
in green with the two clear outliers, dragging the
score down a bit.
And lastly, the handwritten sheets in blue
score lowest with the widest distribution.
Overall, we can see that the model's performance
in especially handwritten sheets, is inherently less
predictable when the writing is unclear.
So we also wondered why certain sheets score worse.
The first one that we noticed that every model guessed differently was
hard-to-read cursive surnames. Because the model cannot reason about it.
There is no fixed vocabulary to fall back on.
That's why every model guessed differently, actually.
And another problem, as we all know, the low-resolution photos.
And other problems, crossed-out redetermined names, like sheet has an
old ID crossed out and replaced with a newer one.
More than
three labels or two--
Models cannot tell which is current, and it struggles actually.
So
there are a few takeaways.
Yeah, transcription accuracy depends strongly on the label type, as we see
here. And we see that the AI transcription
achieves an
average accuracy of 94%, which is great.
And the best value was the Gemini 3.5 Lite.
We saw that the best accuracy-to-cost trade-offs.
And yeah, a local model, Gemma, achieved a
comparable performance without API token cost.
And it's an great opportunity for institutions if they
do not want to share their dataset with open
paid models.
So as a next step,
we want to apply Herbot to a large herbarium sheet collections.
Firstly, on our herbaria, Ghent Herbarium, and yeah,
publish it as soon as possible.
And also we want to implement the OCR part because I can
imagine that some people
doesn't want to use AI because of the hallucination. That I heard a lot.
So we want to also apply the OCR part,
since we have already
a detailed information, like via LabelStudio location
information. So that's also feasible.
And the current datasets are already on this link, but it's not
public yet. In a few weeks, we will make it public before the extracted
abstracts.
So yeah, thank you. Thank you for listening to me.
And also, I would like to thank my team
for
the support, and I wish you a pleasant TEDx
conference.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So we have time for a question or two, so if anybody... Oh.
I'm going to go here, and then I'll go there.
I just have a question for you. How does this system deal with
annotation labels that are all over the sheet and other numbers
that are on the sheet as well, like catalog numbers and
notations and they can have all sorts of information that
may or may not be interpreted in the right fields.
So you're saying that the AI, how interpreted?
Or
did I get it correctly?
Yeah. How does the AI--
Does it make mistakes reading all that information?
Because a herbarium sheet can have a lot of information-
Yes
... that has nothing to do with the actual collection itself. Yeah.
Well, but I mean, and annotation labels are different or have different dates on
them. So I'm just curious how it deals with that.
Okay. I hope I understand it correctly.
For the transcription part, it's more
general, like the catalog number, for example.
We did the prompt
that's suitable for that. It
takes the catalog number and all the information that's on the herbarium sheet.
But for the evaluation part,
we are not that confident because
as I said, if you have your manual annotation, you can still apply that.
But if you are using GBIF Which I showed
already they have a lot of mistakes.
So if you think the catalog number or other information are
correct on the GBIF, you can still use it.
But
as our
experience, we see that a lot of problems with that, and there is no way to
evaluate those results, every information there.
So what we did, we just look at the really important ones, like at the author
name, the taxonomy, and so on. I hope it was the answer of your
question. Yeah.
Yeah. I have a question. Because I
saw you are actually extracting locality and geographics-
Yeah
... data as well. And I will actually bring a question, is
about a habitat. Because quite a lot of
specimen sheets, like herbarium sheets, they actually aggregated the
habitat inside of georeferencing's data.
And they would just basically mess it up in the tags.
And habitat data is actually a field, actually a
free text in the Darwin Core standard.
Yeah.
So you need to fill that in. But it seems like
you haven't actually got it cover in the current data.
The habitat, you mean?
Yeah, the habitat data.
Like in general. Yeah, as I said, for the transcription part,
we do have a habitat part if it's on the sheet.
So for transcription, we really wanted to give all the information, but when
you
go down to do
evaluation parts,
as I said, again, if you have the manual annotation, you can still
compare it if there's a typo, hallucination, and it gives you a score there.
But if you just look at on GBIF, people put extra
information there, and I don't want to penalize AI for it because it wasn't on the
sheet. You know the extra information, you put it yourself on
GBIF records. So that's why habitat is
quite detailed.
And that's why we didn't want to add it.
Yeah.
Awesome. That's all the time we have for questions.
If you have more, feel free to find our
speakers afterwards. English is hard.
Okay. So our next speaker, and thank you so much.
So yeah, our next speaker is also an organizer of this session,
so overachieving.
And Wouter will be talking about AI-assisted
digitization of printed identification keys from book to
structured data in minutes. So welcome, Wouter Apart.
Thank you.
Yeah. I'm going to take you through a little pipeline
that we made to use LLMs to digitize
identification keys and why any of this even matters.
Yes.
Almost all data that we work with is based on
observational data, which means that someone somewhere made a decision
of what something was.
So identification is really at the basis of most data that we work
with. And I've been working with this for a couple of
years now.
I
made an image recognition app, image classification app,
that takes a picture and tells you what species it thinks it is.
But I've also been working with identification keys.
And
a reasonable question to ask is why would you even work with identification keys
now that we have AI, which will just tell you what it is, right?
And that's because it's not that simple.
In a lot of cases, the picture is not going to contain the information that you
need to
reliably identify the species. You may have to look at the shrew, you have
to look at the teeth to really know what species it is.
That's not going to show up in your picture unless you already know what you're
looking at, and you're going to take a picture of the teeth.
Another thing that
the image recognition model doesn't do is tell you why it
is that species. It just gives you a list with confidence scores.
But the domain knowledge of what separates one species from another,
that's embedded within these identification keys.
And thirdly, there is a problem that these fancy
algorithms that we make to recognize species from pictures, they need
labeled input. So we need to know what it is before we start training the
model. So again, we need this domain knowledge, and I think
that's not going to go away. We need both.
However, these keys are hidden in books that are hard to find.
They're hard to use, certainly for laypeople, and they have a very
linear way of working, where if you have
on question number five, you don't know the answer, you're not going to find out
what species it is.
Luckily, we have
digital identification keys.
There's a number of formats. I'm working with Claves.
It doesn't really matter what format we work with.
They solve this problem by making this way more
accessible to a broad audience. They can look fancy, they're
interactive, and you also lose that problem of having to
go one path to find a species.
Like this key, you can choose from several questions to
answer, and you can navigate through what you
can tell about your specimen and find out what species it is.
And you can do pretty cool things with this.
I'm working on something where you can combine the AI with the keys.
So I use the image recognition to tell me
which five species it thinks it may be, and we can use
that as a filter, that list, as a filter on the key
to give me only the questions that separate these five species,
meaning that I can learn a lot more about these species as a
user,
be much more confident about my answer.
And I think this is very educational, but also from a data quality
standpoint, very good.
However, we still need those keys, and they're still hidden in these
books,
if they even exist at all.
So we need experts to make these keys or to extract them from these
books, and that takes a lot of time.
That's days to weeks at a minimum, and experts are
not cheap. I wish I had the funding to get all of these keys,
but I don't.
So we were thinking, could we use LLMs to do
this? And I think about a year ago, the answer would've been no.
It hallucinates too much. It doesn't really listen to your instructions
closely enough.
But I think we now have something that actually works
to a certain extent.
So a little overview of what we've been doing.
This is an example that me and my colleague Stina were working on, on a
rodent key for Norwegian rodents.
So what we did is we downloaded six books on
Norwegian mammals, all of them containing rodents.
And interestingly enough,
neither of these books contained all of the species that we were
looking for. But combined, we have all the species that we're interested
for in our key. So we're making a key that doesn't even exist yet.
So what we do is put it through a pipeline.
We use Claude, but you could use other models as well.
This is just a personal preference, I guess.
We start with OCR. It's been mentioned in the last talk.
Of course, we do this locally.
Anthropic, OpenAI will gladly do your OCR for you.
It's very expensive for you and for the planet, so
please do it locally
and do it once.
So once that's done, we spin up one agent per source.
So we make an agent, and we give it one of those books, and we
give it one simple
task. And that's to find every statement it
can find within that literature
pertaining to the species that we're interested in.
So something like, "This species has densely haired,
not bushy tail hair."
Stuff like that is hidden within that book, and it comes in different
forms. Some books will have classic identification keys, which is really nice.
It's really structured. You can go through it, find these characteristics, very
nice. Other books will only have descriptions.
The same information is hidden in there somewhere.
It's just not formed as a key, but it will contain the kind of stuff that you need
to separate these species.
Very nice books have both, and then we, of course, tell the
model to really look at both. Don't just look at the key.
The descriptions contains extra information that you might need.
Something that we do have to tell the model is to explicitly
also look at the images. So don't just use the OCR version, but
go back to the original key because pictures will
contain clues on what to look for, and
this may not show up in your OCR.
Context is important, so it's told explicitly to go to the
pictures and get out this kind of information.
Another thing we tell it is that a lot of keys have
these statements that are basically three statements or more statements all in
one. So the brown fur, white legs, short tail, this is not
one statement. These are three things, and we want it to be modular and tease
that apart, so make three statements out of this example.
Another thing that we have to tell it to do is try to be as
precise as possible.
A mouse may have in a description a
relatively long tail,
which is very useful if you know all of your mice.
But if you're just faced with one specimen of mouse, how long can
it be?
So we tell it to go to the text and try to find the real numbers.
They're often there,
and in such cases, we tell it to go back to the real
sources
and work in that precise manner.
So
with this,
per book, we have a list of statements of things it found out about these
species. What we then do is we have an audit run by a
separate agent.
So we spin up a brand new agent who's never seen the key before,
never seen the statements, and it has nothing to defend.
This works way better than getting the original agent
to correct its own homework because it's going to defend the choices made along
the way, and it works a lot better to
have a naive agent doing this.
Then we come to the fun step, where we take all of these keys and we start merging
them. And a lot of this is quite easy. You find the same characteristics.
You combine the questions. But it has to do some
more interesting stuff as well. It has to look at the actual content.
Something like pale yellow and whitish yellow is not something you're going to be
able to tell apart in the field. They're basically the same thing.
So it has to know that. It has to combine them.
And every such choice it makes, we have a document.
So we know that it has made the decision that these are the same thing,
and we or an expert can look at that.
It also moves things up the taxon tree.
If a whole taxon, a whole genus shares a characteristic, it's moved
to the genus level.
By the way, we can also have it translate at this stage if we want, not just a
Norwegian key, but we want it in English as well. We can tell it to do that.
We can give it some source material in English, like a good
Wikipedia article with the right terminology. It can use that.
That works really well.
Then finally, we have a grounding step where we take another
fresh agent, and we tell it to go through all of the statements it now has in
the key and see if it can
verify that all of this is somewhere within the original material.
We don't want it to hallucinate anything.
This works really well.
In terms of costs, we were asked to mention this.
Expert, really expensive.
If you have a single key, you can do this for
10 bucks within an hour.
If you have six books, it takes a couple of hours.
I estimate it's within the range of up to $30, which is,
compared to an expert, a no-brainer.
It does not, however, give you a perfect key.
The perfect key has
good illustrations.
We've tried with generative AI. It will fail.
It will look okay,
but it won't be perfect. Like the yellow-necked mouse, the yellow
neck is in the wrong place. So
we don't have a solution for this yet, and that is
why we want to collaborate with experts that will make these good illustrations.
And that's a general thing. This is not a ready-made key.
It's not perfect, but this is something that we can give to a
taxonomist to go through and to
verify. So their job becomes, instead of transcribing and creating
this key, it becomes to
be a reviewer, which is, we think, a very big step forward.
And these keys are quite good and quite usable in our experience.
So
just a short plug, if you want to hear more about the actual key formats, how we
store this kind of stuff,
I'm
hosting a session on Friday as well on that topic.
Thank you.
Awesome. Thank you. We actually don't have time for questions right now,
but please feel free to find Walter afterwards.
And with that, I'll introduce our next speaker, which is Matteo
Conti, who will be talking about AI-assisted
georeferentiation a posteriori
of herbarium specimens, a case study on Italian
herbaria. So thank you.
Thank you. Okay.
It's a pleasure for me to be here to show you the workflow
that we developed to improve the georeferencing a
posteriori of herbarium specimens.
The idea for this project came about a couple of years
ago
when Italy founded the digitization of 12
of the largest herbaria of the country, for a total of about
four million specimens. The project was divided
into four steps. First, the acquisition of the images,
handled by Picturai, then the transcription of the labels,
and then we, a group of researchers and curators,
are working on cleaning the data, align them to the Darwin
Core, and then publish the datasets on
national and international repositories.
Right now, we are in the third phase of the project, and we are
focusing on creating information that answers three
fundamental questions: what was collected, when,
and where. And for the last question, you have to consider
that locality in herbaria often are simple
description of a place without coordinates.
And you know that coordinates are extremely
important for a lot of different analysis.
For example, species distribution models.
So we started a process of georeferencing a
posteriori with different tools,
and the results we got were not so great.
Using OpenStreetMap tonumina teams, we were able to
georeference less than 10% of the tested
records and about 50% using the
APIs of Google Maps. But we will see
later that here, there are some problems.
I've used this tool a lot in the past with way better results.
So I started wondering why the results were so
poor. And actually, there are different reasons, but
the main one is that you have to consider that
these are historical herbaria. So
around 20% of the records are written in Latin.
They're using historical toponyms, and also
almost all the labels are handwritten, and
really a lot of time is almost impossible to read some
words. And this brings to a lot of
transcription errors.
So
to solve this problem and improve the georeferencing, we
started to explore different ideas, and at the end, we
developed a workflow that combines large language models
with geocoding services. This is the workflow.
It has
six steps, and in two of them,
LLMs are involved. And
now I show you briefly the pipeline.
First of all, the locality is normalized and
passed to a LLM detected as a parser.
So it takes the locality, it separates it into its component,
and then extracts toponyms, habitats,
elevations, and geographical relations.
So for example, when you see between place A and place
B or near place C.
Here, we spent a lot of time in refining the prompt that
is divided into three parts. First, the system
instructions, where we tell the
LLM how to parse the string and what to extract.
Then some examples are inserted
dynamically based on some patterns that
are present in
the locality strings, and then we pass a
batch of localities.
And to better understand all these steps, here is an
example of a locality in Latin with the
translation below.
And here the script that passed the locality
to the LLM see that it is in Latin,
so it inject into the prompt at least one
example in the same language. Then it sees that there
are different spatial relations, and so also
inject into the prompt
different examples with similar spatial
relations. And in this way, we are able to greatly
improve the performance of the parsing step.
Then the extracted toponyms are matched against three
different gazetteers. Gazetteers are these
dictionaries containing a lot of different
locality names with the coordinates.
Here we extract up to 10 candidates
per toponym that then pass through a
series of checks where the candidates are ranked,
and the ones that fall below a certain
threshold are removed.
And the surviving ones are then passed to
a next step with an LLM detect
as a judge that compares the original locality
with the candidates and keep only the
best match. The model can keep a single
best match with no reservation, and it is
accepted, or it can keep a single match,
but with some uncertainty. And in this way, in this
case, it flag it as in need for human review.
The model can also choose to reject all the candidates and return
no answer. In these last two cases, we also ask the
model to return a brief explanation of
its action.
Then there is a final step for
localities that contains a spatial relation, where a
script adjusts the coordinate and the related
uncertainty. And this is the full pipeline.
So now we can see some results. Here I tested
the performance of OpenStreetMap's Nominatim, the API
of Google Maps, and our workflow using five
different models, two of them, Gemma and Qwen,
running locally. Here you can see the number of georeferenced
record, and you can see that our workflow more or less
georeferenced the same number of localities as
Google Map. But when we see the correct
georeferencing, the story is completely different.
Here I divided the results into three categories: correct,
coarser, and wrong. And for coarser, I mean when the
model or the tool is not able to georeference
the most specific location. For example, if we have the string
Alberoni Beach, Venice, and the model just
georeference Venice, this is treated as a coarser
result.
From this graph, we can see that
our workflow
running locally and using Gemma is able to produce
more than double of the correct georeferencing
as the API of Google Maps with less
wrong records. It is interesting to see even the
performance of Gemini Flash Lite with a good
number of correct georeferencing and the lowest
number of wrong one. But the
most interesting thing is that both Gemma and
Gemini Flash Lite are really great
judge models because in their runs,
all the coarser and wrong results were
flagged as in need for human review.
So, in these cases, we had no false positive.
Then our last graph. Here I compare the performance to
the estimated price. You can see the good performance of
the workflow with Gemma 4 that is running locally, so
almost at no cost. And you can see even that Gemini Flash
Lite has a great performance,
while costing half of its larger sibling,
Gemini Flash.
So, in conclusion, as you can see,
this workflow can improve the georeferencing of
herbarium specimens,
especially when complex localities are
concerned. And I want to underline that this is still a
work in progress, so there's still room for
improvement. And as soon as possible, I will release the
code on GitHub under the PlantData repository.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank you so much. We actually have time for one quick
question, and it's going right here.
Yes. Okay. Hello. Great talk, by the way.
I was wondering, how did you do the comparison part?
Because
you're just exactly these coordinate numbers.
For example, one kilometer off and 100 kilometer off, from my
perspective, shouldn't be the same.
I was wondering, how did you do the comparison?
You show an
OpenStreetMap, like a percentage?
Yeah. No, I
simply saw the locality that the model
return. It
is what score the same as my review,
and the distance between the
coordinates.
Sorry?
It has to be zero, like the coordinates it produced and-
No, but if the locality is the same and the coordinates
are close,
it depends. I've evaluated every single case.
I treated them as a correct
answer.
Awesome. That's all the time we have for questions, and thank you so much again
for your talk.
Thank you.
If you have more questions, feel free to find our speakers afterwards.
And last, but certainly not least, we have Kenzo Melville,
and
the talk will be about Towards Scalable Trait
Measurements from Digitized Specimens.
Thank you. Thank you.
Hello. Okay. Thank you. So my name is Kenzo,
and today I will talk about trait measurements and how we can scale
them.
So to
start, okay, as you all are aware, AI is being used
widely on images, audio, and many other forms of
data, and one of the use cases is to
detect and measure specimen traits.
For example, the wingspan of a butterfly or the size
and shape of herbarium leaves. But for this,
we are working in pixels, of course, because it's an image.
We would like to normalize it to a metric unit like centimeters or
millimeters so that we can compare them across collections.
And this is mainly the focus of my talk
today. And how can we do that? Typically, for images
which are already taken, we need to use the ruler on the page.
And more specifically, we need to measure a real-world distance in
pixels so that we can convert from one to another.
And this is exactly what we've done.
Some of you may have also attended Living Data last year,
in which I presented the initial work.
This is more like an improvement or scaling up.
But so we annotated a lot of images like this.
For example, this is every centimeter we annotated.
This is, for example, a line of five centimeters.
So not only the location of the tick marks, but also
the value, so how long they are.
And in general, rulers are very diverse, very challenging.
As you can see, this is just a very small selection
of them. And that's why traditional machine learning approaches,
which want to classify or predict directly,
often struggle with the more unique rulers because there are so
little examples, and they are so different from the rest.
But one key idea for our method is that the same rulers are
often reused. I bet many of you will recognize some of these,
and they are very common, sharing a lot of the same
parts. Maybe only the logo is different between institutions.
So we don't want to predict directly, but we want to match
with a known data set of rulers. That's the way the
method will work. So first, we detect where the ruler is on the page
using traditional object detection model.
We crop it out and normalize, basically just make it
horizontal.
And what we then do is we use a similarity model, like CLIP, for
example, which can find similar images in our data set.
So we get a top three of similar rulers.
And because the rulers in our data set have annotated
key points with tick marks, we can then use another model, which is
called a key point matching model, which will compare two images and
try and transform one into another.
And because the tick marks are known,
we can basically transform it from one to another.
So here in red is the transformed prediction, and
that's the way the method works.
And then, of course, there is some post-processing at the end.
The main benefit here is that the method technically only needs
one labeled example of each ruler, but the downside is if
there is a very unique new ruler that's totally different, then,
of course, it will not work.
The improvements made is mainly in the increase of the data set
size. We now have about 2,000 rulers, which
is about 21,000 manually annotated points,
which took a long time. We scaled up to around
350 institutions, and then basically,
well, renewed all of the models used.
And here, especially for the key point matching, made a really big difference
in
accuracy. And then we also added some more post-processing and quality
checks and added some other images from other
domains, but we want to still expand upon that.
And so a comparison of our results.
So I used the old method from last year and our new
method on the same increased data set, which is
also a bit harder because I
didn't check, does every ruler have more than one example?
I just ran it on everything.
And we see a big improvement.
Now 96% have an error less than 1%, and
also in the average and median prediction errors are increased a
lot.
And as before, the main rulers which work really well are
the high-contrast rulers. But now our average
error is around 0.3%. Does this mean it's that
accurate? No, because the method is
matching from the ground truth set.
There is, of course, a manual annotation error because, yeah, it's
impossible to annotate something pixel perfect.
And this manual error is around 0.8%.
So this is like a maximum That we can reach of
accuracy, and we don't really know in which direction is it too big or too small.
And then also when we look at this annotation error
across image resolution,
we see that is
not really influenced by it, which basically means that
my annotations are typically the same number of pixels off, which
is good news.
Then looking at some results, I hope it will be visible here.
So the main rulers it works really, really well are the high-contrast popular
rulers. There are many examples in our database like this,
and they have very high-contrast features,
so they are very easy to map from one to another.
Some other examples are, it's also robust to lower
resolution rulers and robust to some
occlusions, not the full ruler, of course, because of the key point
matching aspect. If it finds a good match on one part of the image,
then the transformation will be correct for the entire image.
And then,
graphing the
accuracy per ruler type, I also saw that the most
commonly occurring rulers and most popular rulers are
performing the best, which is again good news.
And again, because they are very high contrast and
very different. The worst-performing rulers are more of
the simple kind, like these kind of blocks, which
also are not always the same length, the black and the white, I've learned.
And then also when there is a mismatch between
similar type, but not exactly the same.
So then you get
a mismatch.
And then, of course, when only a very small part of the ruler
is detected or a large part of it is occluded, it can also
cause issues.
And then,
I took this method and also ran Segment
Anything-3 to do a simple leaf detection
prompt.
And basically, the idea was to do a kind of proof of concept.
Okay, now that we have the length estimation, we can
just detect the leaves on the page, and then for a
specific family or
genus here, we can check both geographically
and across
different genus or
species,
plot basically the difference in leaf sizes.
And then we can come up with plots like this.
Keep in mind, this is just a proof of concept, and it's a very limited
amount of images. But you can imagine if you would run this on all the
images that are available, this would give a pretty good
average overall.
And so this basically shows the need for this normalization.
If you want to compare across images, we need all the measurements to
be normalized.
And of course, there will be errors in this.
There will be times that the method will fail, but
if you average over a large enough
data set, then it should average out.
And then if you want to digitize new images, you can
avoid all this hassle by including a computer
vision marker like this. It's called an ArUco marker or a
QR code. But of course,
you will need to know how big it is. So, a student of
mine who works in archaeology, a master student, used it
to digitize
archaeological finds and then take one big picture and then
using computer vision, crop out all the different ones,
count them, and also get their size.
By using a marker like this with a fixed real-world size, for example, five
by five centimeters. This is really quick to detect, and
it's really easy, really accurate.
So if any of you are digitizing
any kind of data, please include some marker or do a
calibration beforehand. And as I said, you could also use a QR
code. This has added benefit that you can add a link or a
specimen number or collection number in the QR code as
well.
But of course, right now, there is no
standardized way to do it.
So this is one of the next steps.
It's currently in a proposal on GitHub for the audiovisual
core. It would be nice to have a standard to store this
metadata because you only want to process each image once
or add it during digitization that people can use it.
So this is one of the next steps. Then we also want to look at other
domains.
I've already gathered a lot of images, but I still need to
annotate them and test the method out.
And then, of course, we want to add this annotation somewhere.
And a good example can be the Disco platform because
there you can add annotations to specimens, and then other
people can just reuse them. So once
these length annotations have been made, everyone can basically reuse them or
correct them or add new ones once you have a new method.
And then, of course, we want to combine this with some trait
extraction methods so that we can see how traits change
globally over a large scale.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. Hello. Okay. Thank you.
I think we have time for one more question. Well, sorry, one question.
We haven't had one yet. So if anybody has a question, feel free
to... Okay.
And then after this is lunch, so if you have or want to talk to
any of the presenters, please do.
Hi. Yasin Bakis.
My question is: there is lens distortion in some of
the images. It depends on the equipment, I guess.
So it means that if you put two of the
same scale bars, one in the corner,
one in the center, they show different measurements,
pixel-wise. So did you
come across any kind of
failures like that?
Yeah. That's a good point.
Right now, I didn't take this into account,
but he's correct. When you take an image with most cameras, there is
some distortion of your lens.
So if you don't calibrate your camera, then there will be
distortion in the image. So this means that
this one, let's say it's a 100-pixel line.
If you put your ruler somewhere else, it might be 101 pixel.
So I assume it's a very small difference,
which is why I did not take it into account.
But
I can imagine if you want really accurate measurements, you
would need to retake the images.
Because we cannot know
beforehand how they were taken. So you need a
full calibration set up with a checkerboard.
But yeah, I was planning to do some tests on this.
But yeah, I didn't get the time to do it.
Can I make a comment before I let everybody go?
Yes.
So we deal with this a lot at NASA with our sensors.
We have to know about the focal plane array, the calibration, and actually,
a lot of cameras have a camera model that you can
get the array of pixels and what the distortion is.
So that could also be a potential if you wanted to look into not having to retake
all of your pictures. But with that, are you going to let us go or...
Okay.
Sorry. Two things before
everyone leaves. One is after the session, could all the speakers come up?
We'd like to do a group photo. And the second thing is I have important information
about lunch, which is that it will be on the third floor, and there's a
door outside Hall B. So look for that.
But yeah. Thank you very much,
once again.
And thank you very much to all our speakers today.
It's been a really nice session, and I hope that we will see you on Thursday for
our discussion session, also in the schedule. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Big enough so that I can see without my glasses.
Same as me.
Okay, everyone.
A very warm welcome to you. It's great to see so many of you here.
For those of you who may not know me, my name is David Eagleton.
I am head of data and digital in the Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew, but
I am better known as chair of the BHL Executive
Committee, and it's in that role that I talk to you today.
It's very timely for us to have this symposium, particularly as you
will have heard from the points raised in Nicole's talk yesterday,
and some of the challenges and opportunities that we find ourselves presented with
at BHL.
So just in case you're unsure, this is session SIM08A,
BHL @ 20, a new chapter for biodiversity literature and
data. So this symposium is actually divided
into two sessions, with the first being focused on
reimagining BHL, foundations, partnerships, and future
infrastructure. The second session will then directly follow this
after the break, with a focus on transforming BHL, the data
extraction, semantic navigation, and future
interfaces.
We're obviously very grateful to the sponsors for TADWIG and all
their support that has made this possible. Thank you again.
Other than that, to say that in this first session, our speakers will be
talking for a duration of up to 15 minutes.
There may be an opportunity for one or two questions at the end of their
talks, depending on how we're doing for time, but there will also be a dedicated
space for discussion at the end of the session.
So, please don't worry if we have to hold questions until that
point.
Other than that, I think all I need to say is to please remember to
abide by the code of conduct and be respectful, as I know we always
are. A very good crowd here.
And other than that, I'd like to introduce Nicole Kearney, our BHL
communications director, to set the scene for today's
symposium with Reimagining BHL. Thank you.
Hello, everyone. You get me twice today or twice, sorry,
this week at TADWIG, because I did get the
incredible opportunity to speak yesterday.
David and I are delightful to be opening-- delighted, we are
also delightful, as you've met us.
We are delighted to be opening this BHL symposium today.
BHL is always very well-represented at TADWIG.
Every year you'll see BHL literature, images, data, projects, and
collaborations scattered across the program, across many different
streams. However, it's been quite some time since we've had a dedicated
BHL symposium here at TADWIG, so we're thrilled to be
officially back on the program offering not one but two BHL
sessions, thank you to the organizing committee for allowing that, as well as an
exciting hands-on workshop on Thursday.
We had originally planned to begin this session with the talk I gave yesterday,
building a new foundation for the Biodiversity Heritage Library, but
we did have the incredible opportunity to deliver that talk as part of
yesterday's mini keynote taster session.
That meant that I could share BHL's transition story with the entire conference,
which was wonderful. But as I said, that talk was meant to set the
scene for this symposium and provide some context for the talks
that follow. So for anyone who wasn't there, and to give us a starting
point for today, here's a very short recap of yesterday's talk.
Over the past 18 months, BHL has moved
from being hosted administratively and technically by the Smithsonian
Institution to operating as an independent, globally
governed consortium. BHL now has a new financial home, a
new legal home, new technical hosting, strengthened governance, new
members and partners, and a major platform modernization effort underway.
2026 is both BHL's 20th anniversary and the beginning
of our completely new chapter. After an intense period of transition, we
now have the foundation, resources, and momentum to start
shaping what BHL becomes next. While we are on much
firmer ground than we were this time last year, our long-term future is not yet
secure, but that's why we're here.
We are really excited to hear new ideas, explore new partnerships,
and have the conversations that will shape BHL's future.
When we put the calls out for abstracts for this symposium, we knew that there
would be plenty to discuss, and we were really delighted by the range and the
quality of the abstracts we received.
Today, we'll hear eight fabulous talks across our two themed sessions.
So that first session, this one, is Reimagining BHL, the foundations,
partnerships, and future infrastructure.
We'll begin with Joe Miller, who'll take us back to the original vision for GBIF
and ask what that vision might mean today.
Then we'll hear from Sydney Jordan and Amanda Bozar about the University of South
Florida's new partnership with BHL and their work with archives,
digitized collections, and data extraction.
And then Harris Goo will introduce the Natural History Museum in London's
work connecting BHL with the Planetary Knowledge Base and transforming
biodiversity literature into structured machine actionable knowledge.
And finally, Nikki Nicholson from Kew will explore new possibilities for
semantic navigation in BHL, including ways of moving beyond
pages and volumes towards more meaningful units of work.
And then after the break, we'll return for our second session, "Transforming BHL:
Data Extraction, Semantic Navigation, and Future Interfaces," where
we'll explore how biodiversity literature can be transformed into richer,
more connected, and more usable knowledge from extracting structured data and
uncovering relationships to rethinking how people discover and interact with
BHL.
Yesterday, I described BHL as a living bridge.
We've put down some strong roots, but we are still building.
We don't know yet what exactly lies on the other side or what BHL will look like
when we get there. But I said yesterday that uncertainty is also what's
making this time so exciting. Today's symposium is really about
exploring what is on that other side, and I'm thrilled that you're all here to
explore it with us. We have, as David said, generous discussion time
built into both sessions, partly because my session was moved, so we have more
time than we expected. So really do please ask questions, challenge
ideas, and help us think about what BHL's next chapter could look
like. You can contribute either here in the room or through the Whova
app.
On behalf of the BHL community, thank you to our amazing presenters for
contributing your work and your ideas, and thank you to all of you for being here.
And with that, it's my great pleasure to welcome our first speaker, Joe Miller, the
Executive Secretary and Director of GBIF. Thank you, Joe.
Thank you. Whova said there'd only be 10 people here, but it was
quite
a bit. All right.
So this is
a different kind of talk than I usually give. It's kind of casual.
I hope it's a provocation and to get us thinking and
understanding where we've come in the last 25 years in
GBIF. So we are celebrating our 25th anniversary this year at
GBIF.
And we
as the executive secretary, I spent a lot of time thinking about the past 25 years
and where we can go as a community going forward.
So what I've done here is put together a timeline that's probably incorrect with
leaving out many institutions and events, and this is my
timeline, so I got the stage, so I did it my way, but you may want to do it
different, but I think you'll understand why I did it this way about the fifth or
sixth slide. So I'm going to start out going back to
the 1980s because
perhaps it was the LTER's
community, the ecologists who started collaborating in making
these
consortiums of like-minded researchers and putting them together.
And LTER, from my research, came together in 1980.
In 1993, ILTER, and of course, this is
a very
robust field now with lots of long-term monitoring happening across the world.
Another one
was GenBank, 1982,
with NCBI coming along a few years later in 1988.
Of course, this is the core infrastructure for our DNA
needs.
Next along the timeline is TDWG, right? Do I have the year right?
1985? Right. So TDWG, of course,
the T-D-W-G stands for Taxonomic Database Working Group.
And, as David mentioned yesterday, this was really based on
the taxonomic community coming together.
Of course, this taxonomic work has been happening
across the world, but TDWG was another advance of this
just as the DNA GenBank was an advance.
So all these things are advanced, and I'm picking out some things along that way.
So obviously, very important advance in our community in collaboration and
infrastructure, and this all goes based back to the standard.
Next, I'm going to go to 1992. That is the year I started
graduate school,
and it's also the year I got my first email address.
I always like saying that because it's kind of been downhill since then, but
1992, my first email address. But something else had happened in
that
this happened, the Rio Conference.
And three fora came out of the conference, the
Convention on Climate Change, the Convention on Biological Diversity, the CBD,
and the UNCCD,
Desertification Congress. So this was a big deal in
1992, and there are the prime ministers and presidents of
the parties taking the picture, and we've come a long way, and not
quite far enough, but it's different than 1992.
But that was a big deal
because
we as a community, it's the first time nations came together to really talk about
these issues and
start describing how we can approach these problems.
What's next?
Oh, there's the CBD in 1992. Got the name wrong there.
All right. So otherwise, there's others as well.
I'm a phylogeneticist. My research has always been in phylogeny, so I've been very
interested in phylogenetic trees.
TreeBASE was first started in 1994, I believe.
Other iterations in 2010,
Open Tree, who I
continue to work with, 2012, and project-based storage
of phylogenetic trees. The next step in taxonomy,
Species 2000 Catalogue of Life.
Those dates might not be-- It's hard to say when these things start, but
the ideas of when these initiatives
have come along. So around the same time,
Species 2000 Catalogue of Life and Phylogenetic TreeBASE.
Now we're getting close to
the next thing,
which along the same timeline,
a group of
scientists
came together and
through the OECD mechanism, OECD MegaScience Forum
working group on biological information, made a recommendation to the OECD on
something called a Global Biodiversity Information Facility.
And the subgroup on biodiversity informatics recommends that the governments of the
OECD member countries establish and support a distributed system of interlinked
and interoperable modules, databases, software, networking tools,
search engines, and analytical algorithms, et cetera, that together will form a
global biodiversity information facility.
So that was the starting document of GBIF that
was published in 1999,
and
a few years later, GBIF came to fruition.
This report has a figure that I like to show, and I would like to
see a raise
of hands if you have seen this figure before. Has anyone seen this figure before?
Yeah, a few. Okay. So this is a figure that's in the paper that
I think about a lot.
On the left side, there is the content area
responsible for GBIF. So this is the vision in 1999, and again,
26 minus 25 is 2001, when
we started the secretariat in Copenhagen.
So the original vision there was a catalog of names of known organisms,
biological specimen data,
species bank, in scare quotes, and biodiversity
literature resources. So that was the original vision of GBIF, and that
these arrows in the other box would point to interoperability or something at
that point. Remember, this is where the internet was just coming together, this
thing called the internet, right?
Connecting to GenBank, sequence data,
geospatial data, climate data, ecosystem data, and ecological
data. So that's why I chose those products and infrastructures along the
timeline.
I'll come back to this slide.
So let's go a little bit further down the road.
2001, GBIF was started
in Copenhagen, and so we're celebrating 25 years.
And an important part of GBIF is the national nodes, and many national nodes are
also celebrating
their origins as well. DanBIF in Denmark, 25 years.
Many nodes celebrating their origin as well with GBIF, and
that's a critical part. We now have 70 member nations as part of GBIF's
governance.
What's next? Oh, yes, I wanted to include OBIS in here because around the same
time, OBIS,
a critical partner organization of ours who are focusing on marine biodiversity,
and we work as closely as possible to
make sure the data shared in both networks are interoperable.
2005, GeoBon.
Actually, I should mention one other thing about the
origin documents of GBIF. It does mention the Convention on Biological Diversity.
So the Convention on Biological Diversity, the CBD, is mentioned there in
1991, and there is reference in the original
document and also in the memorandum of understanding the countries sign
that GBIF somehow will support activities
for nations where the CBD, it will do nothing to contradict the CBD.
So that's why I'm including the CBD and also
GeoBon, which of course is another infrastructure that is
aligned to
and currently today helps take GBIF media data and other data
to help support reporting and monitoring of biodiversity.
BHL, 2006, 20 years.
And
Encyclopedia of Life, 2008.
So
you may have chosen different
organizations to put on there,
but it's kind of biased because I was trying to pick out the organizations
that fit into this diagram and look at
where the original vision was and where we are now, and
what are the
sustainability, to be frank, of
various
infrastructures and projects that now are part of this landscape.
So I put them on the timeline there.
So ecological data early on, GenBank, catalog of
named organisms, and put that both for
the phylogeny and also for the taxonomy.
GBIF, biological specimen data. I'm not trying to say that these are the
only things that need to work in this landscape.
Ecosystem data with GeoBon, BHL of course, and also
PLOSI for
literature data, very important to GBIF, and species bank, which
I think in this regard refers quite closely to
Encyclopedia of Life. It's like a database of traits of species-level
things with GBIF, of course, is at the occurrence level.
At the secretariat, we have a clever graphic designer, Javi, so he put
this into this framework. You've probably seen
presentations for the secretariat, who we have this flow from left to right of
the data that is shared with GBIF, how we manage GBIF data, and how it is
used. So we've mapped on to this framework, these
original vision of GBIF.
So we have
a species bank in the middle. Is that gbif.org?
Maybe. Certainly, catalog of
known organisms
is the catalog of life backbone that we now use
in GBIF. So that's connected to the central part there.
We have the standards. I should put Tagwood underneath that, but of course,
standards make this all possible.
And then we have some of the data sources that the original vision thought would
come through with GBIF, such as biological specimen data.
We all know where that comes from, core to GBIF.
Biodiversity literature resources, which we're talking about in the big picture in
this symposium.
Geospatial data, sequence data, and ecological data.
And at some point, all of this data does come into GBIF in some manner,
and GBIF is connected to that. And we do know through the
citation tracking system that the data flow into GBIF is used in
research, and then that research is applied to policy, to the CBD,
and we know some of that is applied to ecosystem data and also to climate
data. So we know that, yeah, I guess the results of the research influence
are about climate implications. So that's the original vision of
GBIF. And then this is the kind of GBIF today,
in which, if you've seen me speak, or someone else from
Secretariat, we show this quite often.
So these are the different data providers, institutional, such as
museums,
ministries, field scientists, citizen scientists, businesses.
Now there are around 300 businesses that share data with GBIF.
Universities, all the various data types, which we're trying to expand.
Specimens, observations, literature, sensor-based DNA, and survey and
monitoring data. The critical requirement of open
licenses and standards coming into the central index aligned with Catalogue of
Life and how it's used for research and policy.
So this
is a question, I guess. Is this what was
intended
in 1999 with that paper? This is the result
of where we are,
from the Secretariat view, of lots of organizations,
projects, infrastructures that are part of this coordinated
graph. That is, we working together
to do what we can to provide data for science and policy.
So this is where we are now, but I don't think it's the original vision
of GBIF.
And I didn't
say this sentence that's in the bottom of that figure, which you probably read
earlier, but it says, "GBIF would enable
synergisms among existing investments that is not possible at
present." So that's in 1999, right?
So I think GBIF does that. We are synergizing,
for example, sequences that are in GenBank come into GBIF.
Museum specimens
have a better
view and are seen and used globally because they're shared through the network.
Same with camera traps. So we are providing the synergisms, but that's
not all GBIF. It's
done through collaboration, and there are many
strengths and weaknesses across that collaboration.
So the original vision of GBIF was to have
more of it together in a GBIF, but that's not what happened.
The original
funders of GBIF scaled back, I forgot to mention this earlier,
scaled back the
breadth of GBIF to what GBIF is known for, species occurrence data, and
also for the Nodes network. It did not have sufficient funding to do the
taxonomy, the
species bank, and the literature. So that was not.
And you can see in the timeline after GBIF was
in 2001,
expanded Catalogue of Life and Species 2000, BHL, EOL
emerged to fill those gaps. So we've been working in this
landscape of trying to tie this all together.
And so I guess I
put to you, as my provocation,
the vision was that GBIF would enable synergisms across this landscape
and investments that were not possible at present in
1999. But as the great
sage asks,
"Is that enough?"
That's my question.
I don't know.
So I hope we can have a discussion about this either now or
in what mechanisms possibly we can move forward to make it
better, to make it that original vision or something better than the original
vision. Thank you.
Does anyone have any questions for Joe?
Actually, can I say one more thing?
Oh, absolutely.
So I'm happy to announce that
as of noon today, we put out a social media post that we have a new paper
published, "GBIF After 25 Years," by Biodiversity
Data Journal, Pensoft. If you go to any of the social media accounts
for Pensoft or GBIF, you'll be able to get a link to the paper, and
it's
a little bit on everything we do at GBIF.
And it's a very long paper, but I hope you find something in there and learn
something new
about the GBIF. So thanks for everybody for--
And I'm happy to say that all the Secretariat is an author of that paper,
and thanks Pensoft for
publishing that. So please see that
or stop by either the Pensoft or GBIF booth downstairs. That's my thing.
Questions?
Overwhelmed us.
So Joe, I guess the question is,
other than it would be nice to sort of recreate that diagram, what's the
compelling reason for, say, a closer link between BHL and
GBIF? How would you sell that to the GBIF Governing Board?
Yes. So
I think this is an argument that I would like to hear BHL
state. I think I have a particular role in GBIF as
executive secretary, and
one thing I have mentioned to several people, and
as many of you know, this is my last Governing Board of the GBIF, which is coming
up. The community really hasn't come to me and
suggested, and
the question is: Is GBIF going to do this?
Instead of
going to the Governing Board and saying, "We as a community
think we need this." And that really is
the mechanism that we need. It's not up to the
Secretariat to decide. Of course, I have my own ideas,
and I think it's a
It's an argument we need to make across all.
Obviously,
before I arrived at GBIF,
we made a considered
long-term collaboration with Catalogue of Life because we were
duplicating
work between developing the Catalogue of Life and GBIF and bringing that together,
and now it's having really great benefit to both of our organizations.
And we're seeing Catalogue of Life and Checklist Bank being mentioned
hand in hand with
GBIF, which is fantastic. So that was a concerted effort,
and
I guess I'm
offering the communities, I would like to hear what the community thinks about that
and the vision going forward.
Is that a cop-out?
No, actually, I think that's exactly what we need.
So as I tried to allude to yesterday, BHL has spent the last
year kind of refinding our feet and developing the foundations for
this new future, and we are now ready to take on those challenges
or at least find ways of making them possible.
The literature is the source of truth, or perhaps the current
state of truth for those scientific names, the evidence
behind the names. And what I've always loved to see and what I know
Rod Page has also wanted to see is that you can link directly from
every single species profile on GBIF and the other taxonomic
databases directly back to the literature.
You should be able to go to a scientific name and click on the literature where
that name was described-
Yeah
... or where the species was described,
and link back. So I think that's always been my dream for
BHL.
Yeah.
There are many of us who think that the scientific names on BHL are the most
important things in BHL, the contextual information around them.
So
I think we need challenges like yours from everyone that we work
with, and we would love to be more of a network of partnerships where we are
part of the biodiversity knowledge graph in a much stronger way than we've ever
been.
Yeah.
I'm not quite sure who had their hand up first.
I would argue
that we are really integrating data
from literature already at large scale.
62,000 datasets in GBIF are from literature.
When you publish a new publication like in Pensoft or an EJT, within
24 hours, all the data is in GBIF.
It's there. It's in Checklist Bank. So we have really this network done.
And the important point is it's not a link to a publication, but it's actually a
link to a specimen, to a holotype. And you go from the
holotype, you go to
the
material citation in the publication to the exact position in the text.
You go to the treatment. You can go to the article.
You can go find out how the specimen has been collected.
So I think we're much, much further ahead in terms of this
integration. Actually, to some large extent, we have it.
So it's more also a question of how to scale up and how can we
bring in our people or the authors, the
scientists, to understand what's happening and to change the way we
publish so all the data they publish is in GBIF.
That said,
some people say a material citation is just a duplicate of a name,
but as Tim Robertson points out, it's not.
It's part of a history of a specimen.
And in many ways, the material citation for about 100,000
species' names is only there because it's directly out of the
literature.
So
the challenge now is how to bring all this data into the
biodiversity knowledge graph. And in fact, I would argue it's also almost
there because all the data is in structured form, we can use
it. And so I think it's really thinking of
where we stand now, how we can bring in
BHL to actually help to expand this.
So it's not so much think about how we can do it, but it's really the challenge,
how we can add up 500 million pages into this
realm so we can go from a specimen cited in the publication
to the place in the publication so we can cite as you do in
science and have the trusted data.
Yeah. As a scientist, I agree with you.
We would love to have and need to have this very detailed data.
Two weeks ago, I was at the Kunming Dialogue in Kunming, which is part
of the CBD process, and got to sit at the tables with CBD focal points
of many countries. None of them mentioned that.
They mentioned the inability of getting any data from their country
into any usable format so that they could use.
So
as a scientist, I completely agree with that, but there's also
the world is burning, and we need to
do. So this is my conflict. I don't have an answer for that.
And the best there would be resources and government
priorities and biodiversity to make that data available,
but there's not. So as GBIF
secretary, it's what can we do at
GBIF to help those
science and the parties manage their data so that they can do
something on the ground. So that's the conflict I feel
when I'm sitting in my office and yeah.
What is the point is that now
within 24 hours something-
Yeah
... published, we have data about how warm it's in GBIF.
Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah.
In that whole related
data.
Hey, good
So,
just to kind of endorse your initial response to Donat
there, but also to maybe double down a little bit on Rod's question
and your response to that. So you said two things.
You said, "Is this a cop-out?" when you responded to Rod.
And I have to say, it sounded a bit like a cop-out to me.
But you
also used the big word, the V word, the vision word,
which I think is really critical here.
Yeah.
That, in a way, kind of addresses the point I think that
you're trying to make with Donat, which is that the scientist in
me responds exactly in that same way-
Yeah
... about the detail and the data. But the reality is,
it's the big vision. It's the sort of 21st
century version of that diagram-
Yeah
... that I think we need.
Yes.
And two
big things, in my view, have changed since that.
Obviously many things have changed since that drawing was put together.
But one is our technology landscape has utterly transformed.
And in parallel sessions throughout this whole week, we have
major sessions on AI really doing things that
were unimaginable just a few TAD weeks ago.
And I think we need to re, if you like, invigorate
this vision with the power of AI,
to think about what those
opportunities are. And I think the other big thing that's changed is
need and the kind of need for demonstrating impact
and the many dimensions by which impact has of this data.
So we can all speak to the value of biodiversity
literature,
Donat's kind of response, which is that sort of scientific response to this.
But I think it's how that translates into policy, how that
translates into addressing actually some of the other questions that we've been
trying to tackle in other sessions, like the potential
commercial benefits of this data and how that might reinforce the
sustainability of some of the infrastructures that we've got.
Now, these are really hard things to tackle, but I think
the answers lie in this community.
So for me, the real answer to the, "Is that enough,
and what next?" is we need to have a deep think within the
community about drawing up that kind of consensus
view of what that future looks like, drawing on technology,
drawing on impact. And that, I think, will
really cement what that next 25 years looks like, both
for GBIF, but also this ecosystem of supporting
infrastructures like BHL, which are absolutely pivotal
to this. So, sorry, that was a bit of a monologue and not a question.
Yeah.
But that's just sort of my perspective on how I think
we'll answer that question by going back out to the community.
So Nicole, I was able to get you back on time, wasn't I, by having a long session?
Well, as I sort of indicated, the fact that I was moved out of the session means we
have so much more time than we expected.
Thank you for that really invigorating discussion.
I'm really excited that we can continue that afterwards.
I do think that Amanda and Sydney are probably very keen to get up, and I'm very
keen to hear their presentation. So I would love to introduce
Sydney Jordan and Amanda Bozarth from the University of South Florida to
share exciting developments in our new partnership with them.
A huge thank you to the University of South Florida Libraries for
responding to our call for support last year, and one of the wonderful
organizations who stepped forward to assist BHL
during our transition. Thank you, Amanda and Sydney.
Thank you, Nicole.
We have a timeline, but it's a shorter timeline to cover.
So the University of South Florida sits at intersections of several
significant and vulnerable habitats in the Tampa Bay area of Florida in the
US. Across the state, public and private institutions
have created over a century of research data to understand
and protect these spaces, much of which has sat closed in
field offices for decades.
Our holdings are primarily historical, ornithological, and marine science data
sets that were primarily collected by hand and on paper.
To frame our talk today, and particularly our partnership with
BHL, I will start with three snapshot anecdotes about
USF's archiving and digitization efforts and our partnerships to
explain why we wanted to join BHL and what we hope to accomplish now that
we have.
First, in 2014, our late colleague Andrew Hughes
accessioned a large collection of records from the esteemed ornithologists Robert
Porter Allen and Alexander Sprunt Jr., housed in the Audubon
Everglades Science Research Center,
in attics in South Florida.
And these materials really launched our environmental collections.
In the team's first digitization and OCR testing, they
were able to provide evidence to the state that declared the American flamingo
as native to Florida. They ended up protecting its nesting habitats
from being developed into military installations, and now the
result is that the bird has been designated as our state bird.
Second, in 2024, and much more disappointing in its
outcome, we were attempting to obtain archives from the
Egmont Key State Park and National Wildlife Refuges.
These efforts had stalled, and when Hurricane Milton landed with an
almost direct hit in our area, the island underwent seven to nine feet of water.
Nearly 100 years of records, including daily bird counts, are believed to be
destroyed.
Third, and a little less dramatic, but no less significant than the previous two,
just last week, we sat down with local environmental journalist Mac Chesnes for an
oral history project about the Tampa Bay estuaries.
One of his reflections about collecting stories through the Bay really struck out
to me
He shared his love for the unique opportunity he had of driving around the
area on a daily basis through one of the most ecologically diverse
estuaries in the state. But he lamented that with the realities of his
travel, being that we don't have a lot of public transit,
resulted in a lot of exhaust from his vehicle and all the other
vehicles, which is the top polluter of those waterways he's writing about
protecting. And so he found himself to be kind of trapped in this circle.
So as you can see, our range of materials and the kind of things we
collect are broad,
but primarily, we focus a lot on stories.
A lot of our records that we collect are not strict data sets.
They're more prose-based. And so these stories
and many others like them have really grounded our work and the partnerships that
Special Collections and Digital Initiatives at USF Libraries have developed,
and they ultimately led us to joining you all here today.
I hope these insights might also explain our eager pursuit of membership in BHL,
as it's a natural fit for us as we share a similar mission to
preserve environmentally significant research data.
Our presentation will showcase where we are now as new members of BHL, and
why we're participating as a strategic partner before discussing the scope of
our holdings and what we hope to accomplish in the years to come.
This had cute graphics, but I
loaded the wrong version, so it's all still now.
So how did we get here? I want to take you through a timeline of
USF's courting of BHL and our symbiotic relationship that we've developed.
As mentioned, we started collecting environmental archives around 2014, and we
were set to formally launch this initiative to the public in March of 2020.
And as we were setting up our exhibit spaces, Sydney and I were called into a
meeting to plan for remote work for some virus that people were calling COVID,
and very frustrated by this distraction of an extra meeting, we finished our
setup of the exhibit after hours that day and were preparing our promotional
materials.
That Friday, we were told we were going remote for the pandemic, whose significance
was only starting to come into focus for us, and our launch didn't happen at all.
In the weeks that followed, we created a digital version of the exhibit and
migrated our promotion onto a virtual hub, which is our Florida Environment and
Natural History portal. We call it FLENH.
And our research for the portal, we ended up coming across BHL over and
over and using it as a possible model.
Unfortunately, BHL was closed to new members, hence the sad face.
In 2022, we attended the American Library Association meeting, and once again
tried to woo BHL, this time at a tabling event at the Library of Congress, and they
were again telling us, "No." Closed to members. Didn't want to work with us.
They did, but they couldn't. They were very nice about it, but we were sad when
we left.
And then when we found out that BHL lost its hosting by Smithsonian just last
year, I filled out the request immediately for support and was
delighted when Kelly Tripe, the transition director, reached out to me about a
possibility for technical redundancy that could be hosted at USF.
We're really excited by the opportunity, and we joined the consortium in December,
and this is where we are now, but we have quite a long way to go.
The strategic partnership and technical redundancy between USF and BHL involves
spinning up a new server on USF's AWS cloud for the
Macaw platform. Macaw is the ingest platform used to get materials from your
institution into BHL. This new instance will allow
for additional redundancy on top of the two that exist, one at
Smithsonian and one for BHL Australia.
And with this uploading alternative, we're hoping to both create
stability and share the efforts for onboarding users to
Macaw between consortium members and BHL's incredible but limited
secretariat staff of Colleen, Bianca, and Nicole.
And I'm excited to announce that USF's Macaw instance has been fully spun up.
Our systems team and our data management team have partnered with BHL's tech team
to get this on board. We're hoping to publicly launch it to our
consortial members in the middle of October and have our first
onboarding in November for a new member.
This creates quite a bit more security for BHL by having an
additional way to continue running the system
separate from the Smithsonian instance.
This effort, as part of BHL's goals for modernization and security
with their new fiscal sponsorship, also offers USF the ability to test our
own goals and expand the reach and usability of our archives.
Sydney, who's the coordinator for our FLENH collections, will tell you more about
that now.
All right. So as Amanda introduced, I'm just going to overview our collections a
little bit. But our FLENH collections currently consist of 38
archival collections, including paper records, recordings,
art, maps, photographs, slides, and field notes, as well
as a robust book and serials collection.
So just generally in Florida, extreme weather incidents and the natural humidity
and heat in the state make archival records particularly
vulnerable unless they're well-maintained in
ventilated and climate-controlled spaces with appropriate housing.
Most of these are not.
So many organizations are forced to store their records in non-air conditioning
attics, storage units, and even marina lockers just
due to limited budget and just they don't have preservation in mind necessarily.
So complicating matters for us is a pendulum of local, county,
state, and federal funding and management structures, which often makes
the stability of our protected lands uncertain.
Let's see. Okay. So our park system, as an example, it
threatens to change hands and lose tax-funded support with surprising frequency,
and that complicates this whole retention and preservation cycle.
So despite these considerations, FLENH's foundations are in place for
us now.
The collections grew sporadically across a decade.
However, a large portion of this timeline coincided with a lack of
dedicated personnel with the necessary archival and bibliographic
processing knowledge to make these collections discoverable.
So after tackling the backlog and preparing collections for researcher use and
digitization, we're now at a good stage to move forward with more
consistency and rapidity, hopefully progressing from the
feeling of this murky gray photograph you see here to a more vibrant and
modern interface.
On the screen, you'll see a comparison of our library's FLN mission alongside the
charge of BHL, and notice overlapping aims, particularly in their
respective dedication to free and openly accessible collections for a
global audience.
Alongside the physical collections housed at USF, we've expanded to
born digital content, including journals.
So our institutional repository has the necessary infrastructure,
personnel support, and preservation plan to absorb online
collections under threat of disappearance or long-term instability.
A major success story was the adoption of the Searchable Ornithological
Research Archive, known as SORA. It was no longer sustainable
by its host, and now USF manages those 87,000
articles.
In total, our digitized environmental collection currently consists of more
than 112,000 records, totaling close to 6.7
million downloads, 4.4 million of which are from SORA.
It's a very small fraction of our total holdings that are online currently.
But we hope that historical information in our archives can provide important
baseline data for scientists, that we can become a destination for
contemporary collection of literature in uncertain times, and that
material in our collection will help generate new scientific research.
So while what I just described is our ideal, we want to delve into the weeds and
share the mess of trees to work through on the way.
Our digital collections are openly accessible, which entails a large amount
of invisible labor. Environmental entities in America are
often jointly managed between divisions of state and national bodies, as
well as involved a lot of contracted workers, meaning that rights
clearances can get complicated. In some cases,
redaction of digital copies must be undertaken when protective considerations
are necessary for environmentally sensitive lands, personal privacy,
or reputational harm.
In addition, by early 2025, USF Libraries launched
large-scale efforts in response to federal changes to our web content
accessibility guidelines. WCAG 2.1 is the
statute. So that means that all of our handwritten materials
requires transcription by federal regulation, and any images,
figures, tables, and charts need alternative descriptive text.
However, the good news is that all of these steps make our content of a higher
quality and in alignment with the mission of BHL.
So here you'll see what our FLN archives look like now.
They're processed cleanly, described in detail, available to researchers,
and ready to format as interoperable data.
During our early testing phase with BHL, I've already uploaded
108 items totaling approximately 2,800 pages,
though the majority of that is currently published material.
A significant portion of our archival holdings consist of handwritten
data-rich documents, such as field notes and warden reports, which
have a mixture of both qualitative and quantitative data in
non-standardized formats. So even those recorded in
prefabrication observation sheets are often inconsistent, as each
scientist has a unique way of capturing their data, and no one likes to stay within
the lines.
We hope to accomplish the ingest of archival materials at scale to
BHL by building on previous workflows established for BHL's Field
Notes project or leveraging OAI-PMH methods like
Biostor does, by incorporating new methods to bridge archival and
bibliographic standards to streamline the process.
The struggle for many institutions is that staffing and skill sets for those
roles tend to be divided across departments, whereas ours is consolidated, so it's
a little easier for us.
And in serving on BHL's Metadata and Cataloging committee, I hope to learn from
long-standing members and help draft documentation to alleviate some of these
bottlenecks and work with USF's data manager to develop crosswalk
solutions.
So with our new partnership with BHL in mind, USF has been
interrogating how our digital collections user base potentially differs from that
of BHL and how to incorporate the needs of scientific researchers into our
best practices, standards, and workflows moving forward.
Aggregated and published data sets currently available tend to be less
comprehensive than those from the raw field notes, often including
species counts while excluding things like temperature and tidal observations,
so expanded sets could be of additional value to researchers.
With user surveys indicating that the top BHL need is improved in-text
searching capabilities, one point of experimentation includes transforming and
appending data sets when ingesting material into BHL.
Extracting data from field notes requires more intervention than born digital and
typewritten data sets. So to meet best practices, collections need to
go through a very extensive workflow that involves evaluation and
processing of the physical records, digitization, editing,
metadata, alt text, OCR, additional transcription for
handwriting, and converting tables into comma delimited plain text.
More yet, not all of these data sets of value in these formats are in
tables. Often, they're in prose.
So while we're only in the nascent stage of testing AI extraction for
data, early observations include significant errors in transcription of
handwritten tabular data that requires substantial human intervention and
correction. So examples include species misidentification
and omission of or erroneous numerals, sometimes as extreme as
reducing a count from triple to single digits.
And we must also ensure that the tables are represented accurately in the
transcription so that a screen reader can convey their original formatting to the
user.
As we continue to test methods, we hope to bring together these many threads,
robust collections, diverse data types and formats, accessibility,
usability, and interoperability to add to BHL's rich
environmental tapestry with the data and stories USF's collections can
offer researchers from our small corner of the global ecosystem.
Thank you for your time.
Do we have any questions for Sydney and Amanda?
Great.
What you described is acting as a very advanced user of
BHL and contributor to BHL.
What was it that triggered you to become an infrastructure
supporter for BHL as a whole?
To take that further step, I think it's because for me,
I'm the associate director for our digital initiatives unit, and I'm trying very
hard to
make sure that things that we do have good
background and infrastructure, that we're not constantly chasing our tail on
forward migrations, which is something I spend a lot of time doing.
And so the opportunity to work with another international
organization to provide that redundant support, which allowed me
to also get support internally that I can
transfer to other work that we're doing, I found to be really useful.
It gave us the opportunity to get more closely connected with
BHL.
And there were certain projects that I really wanted to do related to these
collections that I think the relationship with BHL
will help us do, especially on things like partnering on grants
or other kinds of projects. And so for me, I just saw it as a great bridging
opportunity between our goals, the goals of this really valuable
organization to the field, and a way to give back to that organization
because we are in a pretty unique situation to have as much
capacity as we do at USF.
I would just like to follow that by once again just expressing my
personal, and on behalf of BHL, extraordinary gratitude to the University of South
Florida. As I mentioned yesterday, we were completely at sea last year, and there
was a real balance between putting out a call for
support and not wanting to express that we were asking people to throw money
and support at a sinking ship.
And University of South Florida was the first organization who came forward and
responded to our call for support.
And now we have collaborations with GBIF
and the Natural History Museum in London and Vanderbilt University and
Senckenberg, who all came forward, but you came forward first.
And if you can imagine what that was like last year for us to have
basically our entire rug pulled out from under us very suddenly, and
to have you come forward and say, "We will support, and not only that, we'll
take over a piece of infrastructure that is essential to BHL's
functionality." You mentioned there is an iteration of MACORA at BHL
Australia, which is the project I run.
We're the only other place, other than the Smithsonian, that was able to
ingest BHL material, and the only reason we have one was we were too far
away to use the Smithsonian's
platform. So,
it just took too long for us to upload from all the way down in the
southern hemisphere. So we had one, and now you can look
after the northern hemisphere for us.
Does anyone else have any questions?
All right. Huge round of applause for Sydney and Amanda and the University of South
Florida.
I'd like to now hand over to another organization's representative who we're
extraordinarily grateful for. Hiru Sku, speaking on behalf of the Natural History
Museum in London and another extraordinarily exciting
collaboration providing support to BHL at this time.
Thank you also to Vince and to Ben, who are also on your
talk.
All right. Yep.
Hi, everyone. So I'm Hiru Sku from Natural History
Museum, London. And thanks, Nicole and David, for
invite us for this talk. And basically, for
today is I will try to explain what the NHM
have done for connecting to BHL, helping
BHL for reformatting, and how it actually
connected to the planetary knowledge base that
NHM currently is working on, the biodiversity knowledge graph.
Okay. So,
for this introduction slide, because I think most of you
know better than me on the BHL, so I just
skip it pretty quickly. And
this is actually the numbers, kind of days for
the submission date of the slide. And I hope that the number
is already up to date. And this year is
actually BHL turning 20. So happy birthday,
BHL. And most of the user
have been with BHL for 20 years. They use
more old-fashioned ways to explore the data.
So just click the page and view it and read it.
But
how do you think
machines reading the things? So does machine really reading
things like what human do? So obviously not.
And why this matter
is because publication is basically a huge
storage of knowledge and data. So we
are showing example here, so four pages from a
2002 publication, and it
actually contain 142
raw data, including taxons,
locality, and things. So,
how do you imagine if we try to multiplying this with
64 million pages like BHL have, how
enormous this data set will be?
So,
NHM is actually one of the particular user of BHL.
We have so many research works actually laying based
on the BHL literature, and I'm actually
introducing one of our use cases which my
colleague, Ben, has been working years on.
It's actually led by Neil Burmes, another botanical scientist
from NHM.
He has been working on trait extractions for
around 10 years, and most of the times it's trying to
extract traits from BHL literature.
And we did actually have
lots of works on laying
the data research foundation on BHL.
And
for here, we have shown some of the data matrix and
things that is available here, and the project itself, it
extract 700,000 of traits, terms
from across 81 standardized trait.
And it's actually more than-- Sorry, I'm not tall enough.
And so more than 100,000 of descriptions
covering 60,000 species.
But we are only working on English
literature in the BHL. And how do you
imagine? Think about if in German, French,
Latin, or Spanish, and it only actually covers
17% of the accepted floral plans, but what
about different domains as well? And
it sounds really easy, just work for the workflows.
We just detect trait descriptions, lot descriptions, and
then doing the extraction. But for
computer scientists perspective, for the machine learning behind
it, every single task actually need a separate
model
before the
10 years ago. Yeah. So it's actually
not as easy as we expected,
but later,
we
enter into a new era because
people might have been listening quite a lot for
AI in the past few days, in the tech weeks.
It does actually invite quite a lot of
opportunity to how we actually using the
BHL data as well. So,
as what we have shown here is actually showing
how the transformers, the large language models and
things, opening the opportunity to bring it up
the BHL here more larger scale.
So,
we don't actually need
every single models for every single task and vision
language models as a multi
possibilities for the large language model allow us
to maybe, possibly, we can try to do everything
in one go.
So, to evaluate the possibility, NHM actually
start a prototype with the AWS prototyping
team. Is actually a pretty short
prototyping works. Is four weeks, but we managed to
achieve quite a lot, and we selected two
particular journals.
It's the Botanical Journal, and it's from
across around
the mid 90s centuries, and also the most recent
2017. And it's around
less than 40,000 pages. But
we are trying to see that as what is
achievable for extracting the BHL data and
turn this data into a more structured data ways,
and how it can be transformed.
So,
the data workflows pipeline, basically, is we
use
modern
OCR models and
including plain text as what we already have in BHL.
We try to extract tables, figure, place, and all of
these are actually downloadable, and we combine the MROCR
model with the computer vision models to
try to do identifications on article
title page detection. So that's why we can use
this title page to actually do a chunking of different
article, which is possibly be able to
assign DOI and references to other
publications as well.
And so for the article detections,
we
achieve around 98% of
those of the title page detection.
And if we do actually have a table of contents of the book
and the articleization is actually be able to
achieve around 100%, which is
really amazing.
And
we also try to extract the
entity-- Sorry.
If people know me before, I have been working for Knowledge Graph for a while,
so that's why we try to use the similar
techniques for what we have done before ...
to
extracting the entity including taxa, people,
locality, institution, and habitat from the BHL
literature, and use those of them to
construct a knowledge graph. And the extractions
rates accuracy is actually around the
F1 score is 96%, which is really impressive as
well. And we use this knowledge graph to
construct a graph rack. So we are trying to
enable better semantic search and
multi-hop reasoning. Oh, sorry.
Using the BHL data.
So, this is something we have done in this summer.
It's pretty new because people might think about, okay, so
we keep saying that, okay, so the accuracy is really good or something.
So, we try to be more careful. So we
try to do some sort of benchmarkings, and thanks for the
support for the BHL, especially for Mike and Joe.
They provided us quality of data for doing the benchmarking.
And thanks for Rod helping us as well.
And we have
two different bars here. I think
actually the lighter one is the raw GT, which is we
basically select all of the data across
BHL from balances, from different page type
to different decades and also different
both handwritten type and also the printed text type.
So the raw data is a little bit,
you can see that the error rate is a little bit higher.
And for the lower bar one is actually
we strive our dose of the editorial version.
What is the editorial version? It's actually sometimes
when
human try to do transcriptions, it will actually
expand the context, including some sort of illegible
words and those thing we strike them out.
And for printed text, it's pretty good.
And it already achieve human accuracies
for doing a transcription.
Sorry. I
nearly forgot.
I think the
last bit is actually 62% out of 12%.
One, I really want to highlight that.
That is actually where we will actually test both
for Mistral 4, Mistral 3, and Shengja.
And all of them, actually, all of this OC
model actually have a word level confidence,
which is be able to actually let us to do a summarization
to see that whether our model, the current AI model,
is confident on transcribing the data.
So this is actually a really good slight things, and
it actually tried to creating a barrier for us
for before ingesting all of the data back to
the BHL and making sure that if
the confidence score is not that high, so maybe we can
possibly add some sort of
human in the loop testing or maybe the validation on it.
So instead of just getting back all the
AI hallucinated stuff data back to BHL,
but we add extra barriers to it to protect the
BHL data.
So here is actually their prototyping interface.
It's not actually the final version, but it's a
more
older version. And
it's from last year, but basically that's what we introduce
for the prototype is we include
actually the summarizations for the BHLs, which
is actually improving the accessibility as well.
Because sometimes when people reading the BHL
pages, they can't actually read it, it's for the page only.
Sometimes they probably need a text version or transcribed version, so
it might probably be
easier for some
more people to actually assess the data.
The page on the right one is actually
basically we create some sort of visualization ability
for showing different type of entity.
I think it's actually a page from Argentina
publication. I'm not pretty sure.
Sorry. Yeah.
So what this actually enabled,
yeah, we keep saying about transcribing could
bring some more functions to what BHL data can be.
So with this,
I will try to summarize it in three things.
So first, better search is really obvious, as we
already mentioned, because we have the graph rack, and we have table
of figures. So it actually provides more potential
for people researching BHL data. And we also got the
entity, which is making much easier for
the BHL to try to be connected to some
other
external data supplier. And
it's something in
the next slide. But we are actually in the production
phases. We are actually extracting specimens identifier
as well, which is be able to link it back to GBIF
in some point. And
the last bit
is actually
helping people to actually do some sort of research question
analysis, like text mining or maybe some AI
tasks
or some of what I have learned for this Tech
Wag is actually the trust of knowledge is
more of the cultural heritage things.
I've been keep hearing people saying that, okay, so
publication and literature is actually their trust of knowledge,
the foundation of it. So we are hoping
our introduction of all these prototyping things can
actually help to improve this side as well.
So as already I mentioned this,
it's really good news that actually we promoted
our prototypes to the BHL, and they are really happy on it.
And so now we are actually already move it to
the production phase. So we are currently already doing
the re-OCRing about the whole corpus.
And
we will be doing annotations about
Open Golden Standard dataset, which
we'll try to annotating all of the
entities we mentioned there, and also
specimen identifiers and also
the stratigraphy datas as well. And
I will come back to it later, no worry.
And I
will just be quick for this one and next one is--
On
the right-hand side is actually how a literature can be actually look
like as a knowledge graph linking to all of the possible taxa
and our institution and collector and countries.
So, and this introduce to what we mentioned about the
planetary knowledge base because we keep hearing in the past two
Tech Wags or three Tech Wags about a huge
biodiversity knowledge graph.
And, oh, sorry.
This is what NHM is currently doing, trying to build an
AI-powered system, more infrastructure
that's orchestrating
both foundation model and all of the knowledge graph.
And
I don't actually have many time to cover it.
So, if anyone interested in the PKB,
please go to Vince Smith talks for more
detail.
And basically, the last slide is actually
the planning about the production
phases. So we are currently doing some sort of
re-OCR of the BHL whole corpus, and we aim to
actually get done by the end of this year, hopefully,
at least maybe January of 2027.
And in the early 2027, we will be
publishing Open Gold Standard dataset.
And
in Q2, we will be
bringing the Explorer online and
more details that you can go to the workshops and Nicole
and Rod
arrange.
Very last slide. Thanks
my teams, and thanks for Mike, Joe, Bianca,
Colleen, Nicole, and David, absolutely.
And thanks, Rod, for the discussions, and thanks for
our AWS team, Daisy, Emily, Pete, and
everyone. Yeah.
Kee Harris.
We don't have time for questions for this one, I'm afraid.
But again, thank you. So I think we'll move to Nikki,
if that's possible.
Huge thank you again to NHM with your enthusiasm for this project and for your
joining on the BHL Tech team, often you both and Ben.
It's also lovely to have NHM and Kew finish this session.
We started with our newest member, and now we're going through our founding
members, NHM and Kew, both one of the 10
founding organizations that started BHL.
Introducing Nikki Nicholson from Kew. Thank you very much.
Longtime supporter and always doing exciting projects.
Thank you.
Yeah, that's quite an act to follow. I really enjoyed that talk.
Yeah, so Nicole and David
invited me to talk here, and it's a real pleasure to
always talk in support of BHL.
So we wanted to talk about the different ways that one could navigate or carve
up the BHL corpus.
But I've come here from Kew today, so it's traditional that I show this
picture.
So my background with BHL is that
one of the first projects I worked on at Kew was the International Plant Names
Index, and that was funded by a legacy from Darwin,
who at the end of his life, he started to think, "Well, there's
a bit of a data deluge. There's too many books.
They don't all fit in one room in my house anymore.
I'll leave Kew £250 a year, and they can make an index
into these books so that we know where new plant names were published."
And it didn't take four or five years, and it didn't take
four times £250, and we're still doing it today.
It's our longest-running project.
But if he could look forward into where we are now,
he would be amazed with BHL. Not just an index, but
actually the pages that you can look at and inspect.
And that botanist can do that all over the world.
They don't have to come to the library in Kew to look at that important information
anymore. It's there in BHL for them.
But the way that we have indexed into that literature is important because it's not
Just the way that someone might index in bibliographic
terms, because we go exactly to the page that we're interested
in and exactly to a structured data representation on that page.
So we don't go to an article,
although the article is the unit that often is used in bibliographies, and
it's the thing that we address with DOIs and so on.
We go to the exact page, because
some of my colleagues are very prolific, and they write articles that are 150 pages
long, and we can't expect them to
slowly page through everything and find it.
So if we think about the way that we've built BHL, then
I would say that largely it's been populated as a library.
So we've scanned the physical resources that partners have.
These are the things that sit on shelves in libraries, series,
runs, and issues.
And we've generated digital resources from them.
So we've photographed their pages and OCR'd them,
and then we've run post-accession processes.
So we've turned them from just undifferentiated sets of pages
into a set of pages which form an article.
That's the work that Rod's done with Biostor.
And then once we have articles, then we can address them in the way that we do,
in terms of any kind of bibliographical library
project would do this.
But that's really focusing on the library part of the Biodiversity Heritage
Library. And it could have been a
heritage library of quite some other scientific domain, and
we probably would have gone through much of the same steps there.
We have, of course, indexed into
the scientific names that are in
the literature. But this is just to the text of the names rather than
the structured entity that is represented by the presence of that name.
So if you think about BHL as a biodiversity data source, so focusing on the
first word rather than the last, then
our publications are really, really highly structured.
So
last week, I presented
Q's work, and part of that was BHL at the Hypertext Conference in London.
And they were absolutely fascinated to look at biodiversity publications in
terms of how richly structured they were and how many
potential links they had out to other information.
So we have tons of entities in these literature data
sources,
things that we use in other initiatives and that we assemble in other databases.
So we've got databases of taxonomic treatments, things that are in Catalogue of
Life, and they're indexing back into literature that we have in BHL.
And that's the same for all kinds of things like specimens, the way we
identify specimens, either with keys or illustrations,
the things you do with people. So that's stretching out into digital
humanities and history of science research,
and the way we understand where our specimens
and species exist. So spatial data, things like
gazetteer entries and so on.
So I'd scan through
some different pages in BHL to show you this kind of thing.
So
there's a pointer, right? We're still indexing into pages
numerically here, but
this page, it's basically a printed out database, isn't it, before
someone had database access.
So it's an entry of a person. There's tons of structured
data about that person, and it's organized alphabetically.
So that's about people.
We have the same kind of thing with glossaries.
So this is a multilingual glossary, again, organized alphabetically,
definition of a term.
There's a whole run of these terms in English, then a whole run in French,
so you can translate between the two.
Yeah, and the next one is a spatial. This is a gazetteer.
And we've got entries for places, again, not organized,
not
the most easily accessed through the unit of the article, but these
kind of entities, the kind of thing that Gurjeet just showed us, we should be
able to get at them
this way.
So if you think about how we would build a type data resource,
I guess
broadly there might be two choices.
So one could build it from the bottom up,
go across all of the 64
odd million pages that BHL has,
inspect the page structure, find repeated layouts, find entities,
build up from the bottom.
Or you could carve it up and go top down and be more specialized and diverse.
You could say, well, specialized communities index into this data.
They're the ones that are going to be the most efficient at
making those gold standard data sets about how these entities
should be recognized.
So go out and talk to those communities,
see what they're interested in,
how those data are used, and how they address into it.
And I guess a bit of this is a bit like Gurjeet just showed at the NHM in that
Neil Brummett,
being a botanist, he wasn't looking at all of BHL.
He was just looking at the bits that engage botany.
So he kind of focused on that, and then they worked towards it.
So
we've kind of got diversity within our user communities, too, and we should never
forget that.
But if you look at what we've done right now, we're at BHL at
20.
GBIF is at 25. So what did GBIF do with those extra five
years?
So if we look five years back,
GBIF just released the cluster mechanism, I guess,
'21 or something like that.
So
GBIF for a long time, I think, kind of chase numbers, build a big
resource,
and then once that resource is there, you can stitch it together in more
interesting ways. So we can say that we know that these occurrence records come
from the same collecting event, and let you stitch them together, allow people to
navigate between resources in GBIF, not just look at a huge number
of data points that are there.
But this is the most interesting thing, I think,
that we can take from
GBIF to BHL, in my opinion, is the way that the hosted portals have been
developed. So GBIF has got huge amounts of data, 3.8
billion records. Is that right? 3.6, something like that.
But there's these branded interfaces into them.
So as a user community, you can say, "These are the bits that I'm
interested in," and target your attention and your
community to those.
And I think that
probably
drives a bit of friendly competition and innovation between
different projects.
So if you look at the
hosted portals that are available for GBIF, then they're split up in a lot of
different ways. You've got things that are scoped to different countries,
and you could imagine that
there are
similar analogs to that in GBIF. So people are going to be interested in
different--
Similar analogs to that in BHL, sorry, people are going to be interested in
particular subsets of the data. So everything that relates to a country,
everything that relates to a time period, a person,
that kind of thing.
So we could do this same kind of thing to BHL, and then
you get
basically pre-filtering. So this is the Disco hosted
portal in GBIF,
the Disco UK one, sorry.
It's interested in
specimen records that are being mobilized from the UK.
So you don't have to search against the 3.8 billion records that are in
GBIF.
Your search is pre-filtered onto the thing that you're interested in already, which
is specimen records from the UK.
And you can style it the way you want, and it's a place for your community to be
and
talk about other
things that you do. It's not just this view onto the data, but it's also
pages about your meetings, your literature, the things that you're working on
at the moment, that kind of thing.
And the reason why I think it would be useful for BHL is I've often
found this to be--
I understand why this happens, and it's
a problem that probably we could overcome.
So there are data contributors into BHL who
contribute the metadata,
but their funding requirements are such that they want their own branded interface
when they show the data itself.
So Madrid, for example, contributes thousands
of really useful volumes, but you cannot look at them
in BHL itself because they want this kind of nice
branded interface.
And
people are always going to want things like that, that's what funders like.
But this
model that GBIF have built and provided is a way that you can
serve that need for a funder, and you can also serve that need as a user
community too.
And I would glibly say, we always say don't judge a book by its cover,
but we're human, so we do. So we say,
the cover says, "Is it relevant for me?" And really what a funder wants to know
is, "Does it acknowledge my investment?"
So yeah, I'd say to end then,
if we let user communities define the things they're interested in and
carve up subsets of such a large corpus as BHL has
mobilized, then
we can serve a more diverse range of needs.
And I think it really will drive innovation because we will have friendly rivalry
between each other.
Thank you for allowing me to talk today.
That was fabulous. Thank you, Nikki. Questions? Oh.
Thank you, Nikki, for bringing up for the first time the word treatment this
afternoon.
Sometimes it's also interesting
to listen to what's not said. And thank you for bringing
up the hosted portals.
One of the really interesting thing in and what GBIF did for the publishers
is to create hosted portals for journals.
And there are about 25 hosted portals for journals like EJT,
ZooKeys, and many others, which essentially show you
what's in the publication. So you can make a map, and it's not just a map
of
observation points, but each observation point is linked back to the treatment, is
linked back to the thing. So
there is an interesting way to actually create structured data that
can be reused and is actually being reused at large scale.
So look at, if you have a chance, go to
GBIF and look at GBIF, the hosted portal,
and I think it's also a challenge for both for the
using the AI to extract data from
the BHL, but also BHL to see that they can bring the
data into GBIF.
Yep. Thank you.
So Nikki, that was brilliant. It's a great challenge, and I think we'll try to--
In our hosted portal framework we call TaxonPages,
it's a great challenge to us to do that.
So what I see we need is new API endpoints to
BHL, right? So that we can basically do what we used to call
a mashup
... of those things. And I think that goes all the way back to what
Joe's pointed asked at the very beginning.
Joe, I think in your picture, and you asked what's next,
it's right there in front of us. It's all those arrows that are going back
and forth. Those need names and formalization.
All those joint arrows, right? And what we're talking about is an API to BHL.
The kind of things that you heard Donna talk about, link back.
Those are the APIs that make all of these wonderful things happen, and a
formalization of those things for BHL, the
way we talk back and forth, how we process things in the middle, be it a large
language model or a server-side model, et cetera.
Those are the kind of units that might take us to the next generation.
And I think
you gave us a great point. I want to see all these pages.
I want to visualize them in cool ways.
I want to overlay specimen images and distributions, but I need an
API for that, right? A bit of structure, right?
So I think it's all connected here, and
somebody said it already,
but the answers are here in this room somewhere.
Fabulous. I think there are enough brains in this room to solve everything.
Any other questions?
Or any other questions for any of the speakers or continuation of discussions we
were having earlier?
Well, I can keep talking, but you probably don't want to hear from me.
Oh, here we go.
So I was going to make this comment during Joe's talk, but I think it actually
works well here.
I'm reminded actually by the way that eBird started.
So if you all remember when Steve Kelling first came to TADWIG and
was excited about being part of the TADWIG community, and we all
wanted eBird to do everything. And Steve
said, "Nope, we're going to keep
species identification out of eBird." And they
did eBird, a couple of iterations before they started Merlin.
They did Merlin. They did it really well. Well, guess what?
Now Merlin is connected to eBird, and all of that actually
enabled and was a model for what iNat now does, what iNaturalist
does. So I think what I'll say is that the GBIF
approach of scaling back to
the core thing that they thought they could tackle early
is why it is so successful now, because they focused on the basic
requirements. BHL did the same thing.
BHL focused on its basic requirements.
I like the analogy of building it as a library.
That was where it started. But where are we going now?
Well, people like Vince and NHM are picking it up and now
creating a knowledge graph out of it.
So the challenge, though, is how do you sustain all of it, all of the pieces?
And,
I would say, actually, in response to the API point,
now we need
MCP servers so that agents can stitch it all together, and we
just need to
leverage those institutions that have a special interest, like South Florida, to
mobilize for their own personal needs because they see an overlap in mission.
And it's really, I think,
pointing out the value of all of this, and Nicki, you really
brought that up very nicely, is that
users and funders both need to understand how does this enable the work that
I'm doing going forward,
and what do we need to keep it going?
And so,
I don't know where I'm going with this. There's no question here.
I guess I'm just trying to say we all have a part in expressing what
is our value statement, and how can we convince our
institutions to take the piece of it that's most relevant to us
and keep it going.
Thank you. Sadly, I'm going to have to pause our discussions for now because we're
almost at time. Encourage you all to come back and join us for the second part
of this session, which is transforming BHL data extraction,
semantic navigation, and the future interfaces.
If you do have an essential clash this afternoon, we will
understand, but please come back and join us on Thursday morning
for our hands-on workshop, which will be run by Rod Page.
And again, I'll be helping with that.
Massive thank you to all our
speakers today who come from organizations that I mentioned
yesterday are part of the incredible network holding BHL up and
moving us forward.
So it is exactly 3:30, so thank you very much.
Enjoy your coffee and please come back after the break.
Pulled on a dress in a rush.
Mascara on the sleeve, still good enough.
He left my last text on read.
So I took the whole bottle instead.
Bag full of wristbands and gum.
Train platform humming under my thumbs.
I kept your hoodie in my tote. Shouldn't
have let anyone know.
Another missed call.
And I'm swaying through the gate like I don't care.
The Ferris wheel spun red.
While the little white pills kicked in there.
Colors bleed, the edges fray.
Faces I don't know start to sway. The
world distorts, a twisted hue.
Is any of this really true?
Out where the party is. Tripping between fire and bliss.
Somebody leaned in for a kiss. Lifted me up, I was sky high like
this. Over a sea of heads. Saw your green shirt, silky threads.
I dialed in a call. You looked at it, then let me fall.
Another missed call.
Looking for a corner to disappear.
Ferris wheel turning slow. Little blue pill
started kicking in here.
Colors bleed, the edges fray.
Faces I don't know start to sway. The
world distorts, a twisted hue.
Is any of this really true?
Colors bleed, the edges fray.
Faces I don't know start to sway. The
world distorts, a twisted hue.
Is any of this really true?
Colors bleed, the edges fray.
Faces I don't know start to sway. The
world distorts, a twisted hue.
Is any of this really true?
Colors bleed, the edges fray.
Faces I don't know start to sway. The world
distorts, a twisted hue.
Is any of this really true?
But yeah, I think
in my head at least, a real sense of things actually emerging around some
aspects of that big vision.
Because I've been separately pushing you for months to get a return
on all this. So I think that
integration talks as well, as you can see, had an opening
of
basically that invitation from the community around BHL.
We've got a clear value statement about where BHL
sits and how it exists as an absolutely central.
We've got models of how that might start being integrated
into other networks and
sorts of data approaches and things.
So
I think, yeah,
it's super exciting. I just think what
we can really do is to really, as you said,
think about why some of the insights that we should really have
shared and why that integration has to walk alongside the
party.
A bit like that joke, that little smile
is about that proposition there. Do you think that broad
scope-
Yes.
There's just a clicker, and it'll just automatically appear.
Okay, so I can put my computer here?
Yeah.
And it's just-
Okay.
It's all in working quite well.
And there's, yeah, there's water.
You can screen it this way.
Hello, everyone. Welcome, and indeed welcome back if you were with us
for the earlier session. This is the second part of our
two-part session for SIM 08. This is 08B,
entitled BHL at 20: A New Chapter for Biodiversity
Literature and Data.
And this second session will be focused on transforming BHL data,
data extraction, semantic navigation, and future interfaces.
For those who weren't at the first session or haven't encountered me yet, my name's
David Eagleton. I'm head of data and digital in the Library and Archives at Kew,
but I'm also better known as the current chair of the BHL
Executive Committee. And it's our great pleasure to be here today and
have a BHL symposium with you all at this particularly
critical and key time for BHL as we examine the
challenges and opportunities that are presented to us.
You will have heard Nicole touch on this either earlier in the session prior to
this or as part of yesterday's opening taster sessions for
TWIG.
So thank you very much for joining us, and thank you to those speakers who are
going to be taking part today. Each speaker in this session will have 10
minutes to speak. There may be time for one or two quick
questions, but it's possible we may also hold questions until
the end. We will keep you posted on that.
But I'd now like to proceed without further ado and hand over once again to our
BHL communications director, Nicole Kearney, to introduce this
second session on transforming BHL. Thank you. Nicole.
Thank you, David. Again, David and I are very excited to be having this symposium
and to welcome you again up to the stage.
For those of you who joined us for our first session, a huge thank you.
We had a fantastic set of talks and a really rich discussion, which will hopefully
continue this afternoon. For those of you who are joining us for the first
time in this session, a huge welcome.
I know that our first session clashed with some really exciting TWIG sessions,
which I also would have loved to have been able to attend.
Many of our BHL colleagues were speaking in other sessions today.
So I'll give you a quick recap of our first session.
So in session one, which we titled Reimagining BHL, we looked at some of the really
big questions shaping BHL's future, where it sits within the global
biodiversity infrastructure landscape, how some of our new partnerships are
strengthening and extending BHL's role, how the planetary knowledge base at
NHM could unlock new possibilities, and how we might navigate and
connect BHL in entirely new ways. This second session, which
we've called Transforming BHL, will take us further into the content itself and
into the question about how the knowledge locked within biodiversity literature
in BHL can be extracted, structured, connected, and ultimately made
more useful.
We'll begin with Christian Bühling, who will look at extracting structured
biological occurrence data from historic scientific literature and the
possibilities for automated approaches.
We'll then hear from Gerwin Kasperek, who will take a closer look at some of the
challenges involved in turning unstructured legacy literature into
research-ready biodiversity data, including synonymy, co-reference,
and the role of LLMs. And then Regiane Hoffmann will then take
us beyond text alone, exploring multimodal knowledge extraction
from historical entomological literature, and how information contained
in both text and scientific illustrations can be brought together in knowledge
graphs. All three of our first speakers are from Germany.
We've actually got a really wonderful contingent from Germany for BHL.
They're very well-represented in Europe.
We'd love to have more
partners in Europe, but it's very exciting that they're all here.
And Senckenberg is our most recent BHL member who joined us earlier this
year.
Finally, Rod Page will bring many of these threads together, exploring how
extracted and connected knowledge can be surfaced through BHL
interfaces from search and navigation to maps, entities, images,
and AI-assisted discovery, which will lead us beautifully into the hands-on
workshop he's leading on Thursday.
I'm always a bit nervous introducing Rod because he usually completely changes his
talk from what he submitted in his abstract, so he could be talking about something
completely different. Whatever it is, it'll be exciting and visionary.
We've set aside time for discussion at the end, so please do bring plenty of
questions and ideas, either here in the room or via the Whova app.
A huge thank you again to our speakers for sharing their work and
to all of you in the audience for being here and contributing to our conversation.
Before we do begin, just a quick note about our first speaker, Christian.
He's here with us in Oslo, sitting at the back, but he has pre-recorded his
presentation. He won't take part in the in-person discussions at
the end, but he's very happy to answer questions through the app.
So if you have questions for him, please do submit them there.
And he's also very happy to talk to you afterwards in the breaks.
With that, please welcome our first speaker, virtually, Christian Bühling.
You can clap.
Enabling scalable approaches for the extraction of species occurrences data
and related data from historic scientific correspondence.
Legacy documents of various origin and purpose are a rich
source of biodiversity information.
For example, the reports from four meetings of the Berlin
Entomological Society, held from January to March
1915, detailed dozens of observations from
various taxonomic insect groups, some highlighted on these two example
pages from the report.
The accounts often featured detailed information on where and when the
specimens were found, remarks about noteworthy morphological or
physiological traits, and about the collectors of the specimens and their
collections.
As such, these sources are an invaluable and largely
untapped source of biodiversity data.
However, while the three basic information facets of
what was observed and where and when provide the basic pattern
of the accounts, the information is expressed in highly
variable linguistic forms, is often context-dependent,
and varies considerably in detail between accounts, as is
expected for natural language sources.
The overall goal of our project is to evaluate if and
how machine learning approaches can be used to extract occurrence and
related biodiversity data reliably,
at scale,
and in data formats suitable for computational knowledge engineering
As a first step towards this goal, we have assembled an annotated
reference text corpus of historical scientific correspondence.
The corpus consists of digital copies of the source documents,
manual annotations for reports of species occurrences in these written sources,
and a corresponding dataset of occurrence instances serialized in
RDF.
RDF structure is based on a conceptual data model that is aligned with the
annotation model and is aligned with the Darwin Core Standard and with
Wikidata and GBIF data schemas.
For the corpus, we concentrated on the journals issued by the Museum
für Naturkunde Berlin, the Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift,
Zoo Systematics and Evolution, and Fossil Record, and the
predecessors of these journals.
While the journals from their inception have been international journals, they
are expected to contain numerous references to objects contained in our
collection and to research based on our collection.
That makes these journals particularly relevant in the context of our collection
digitization and development.
To compile the corpus, we first identified bibliographic data
and sources for digital copies of the articles.
We then set out to harvest all available full texts, which
involved an iterative multi-step strategy with both automated
and manual approaches to deal with problem cases.
From the available full texts, a random, proportionally
stratified sample was chosen for further annotation.
In problem cases, which were not uncommon in articles originally published
before 1970, a new OCR layer was generated.
Note that for the Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift, and especially Zoo
Systematics and Evolution, the number of full texts that could be
obtained from both open access and access-restricted sources
is, for a number of reasons discovered in the process,
significantly lower than the number of articles published.
The tag set we developed for annotating a biological occurrence mentioned in
the text includes taxon, place,
date,
habitat,
quantity,
person,
and material to mark the text elements describing the
corresponding facets of the reported occurrence.
The occurrence itself, expressed by these semantically related text elements,
is anchored in the source text at the position of the first character of the taxon
name in question.
In our model, taxon names and at least one of the elements place and
date are regarded as strictly necessary for a valid occurrence report.
The tags implement the text-related part of the conceptual data model
that determines the characteristics of occurrences and reports of occurrences,
shown here in an overview.
Each of the tags can be mapped to a corresponding term in the Darwin
Core standard so that identified occurrences can be described using
Darwin Core terms.
In the first leg of our annotation campaign, we identified nearly
1,600 occurrence reports from 165 examined
journal articles.
Tag frequency falls roughly into three categories.
Places are reported in almost all instances.
Dates, persons, quantities, and materials are reported
roughly in a third of all instances, but not necessarily in the same
instances.
Information on habitats and about the location and identity of preserved
specimens using the org and ID tags is given in only
a small number of instances.
Annotations were created using the Inception platform.
The raw annotation data in the Inception-specific data format
is exported for subsequent standardization and enrichment of the
extracted occurrence records.
Specifically, the workflow attempts to match annotated
geographical place names with corresponding entities in Wikidata
over the Wikidata API. The matching was successful for
1,215 out of
1,333 place instances.
For the 681 distinct place entities identified in
Wikidata, the occurrence dataset was enriched with linked
geo-references and geographical context.
Similarly, annotated taxon names were matched to GBIF IDs.
The matching was successful for 1,041 out of
1,154 taxon instances. For the
741 distinct taxonomic entities identified in GBIF,
the data could be complemented with scientific taxon names, taxon rank,
and kingdom.
As a final step of the workflow, the extracted, normalized,
and enriched occurrence data is converted into a graph-based
serialization using RDF, RDF Schema, and related
data schemas. In summary, we have compiled a
comprehensive set of digital full texts for the journals issued by
Berlin's Museum für Naturkunde. It is complemented by a
manually annotated reference dataset of occurrence reports in a
sample from the overall full text collection.
The verbatim occurrence data is aligned and enriched with norm data,
is linked to the original text, and serialized in RDF
for versatile downstream data use.
Data structure is governed by a fit-for-purpose data and annotation model
that is fully aligned with the Darwin Core standard.
The workflow to obtain full texts and refine the data relies on a number
of scripts that can easily maintained and can be scaled and adapted for other
sources.
I would like to quickly address also a few of the challenges we encountered
and which are likely to be of concern in similar projects.
Document retrieval was indeed much more complicated than we had
anticipated in the beginning.
Different bibliographic databases hold different information on the journals
that is, in part, incompatible or incomplete.
To resolve these inconsistencies, it would help to have clear criteria
when a periodical is regarded as the same or as a different
publication by a bibliographic portal, and likewise for the links to
related journals like predecessors.
For this project, we relied on open access portals for historical texts,
in particular the Biodiversity Heritage Library, as well as
access-restricted repositories to ensure we get as much coverage of full
texts as possible.
However, even when using suitable text and data mining licenses, we
experienced erratic behavior of APIs operated by publisher
sites, which resulted in considerable additional work to retrieve full
texts.
When attempting to work with large sets of legacy documents, simple
access and download routes are clearly the more efficient option.
Annotating occurrences in the original sources has been challenging, not only
because it is very demanding to maintain consistent focus for a human annotator,
but also because of the large variability of linguistic forms used to express
occurrence information that has no clear boundary to other types of content,
like deliberations about the distribution of species.
Also, there are a number of knowledge gaps and semantic inconsistencies when
trying to interpret the verbatim information with respect to other structured data.
For example, matching historical place names to contemporary administrative units
accurately requires, in our experience, context and expert knowledge
that varies greatly case by case. We hope to build on this work
by extending the corpus quantitatively with more sources and
qualitatively with more entities and tags, and using the
corpus to evaluate and fine-tune AI-based relation
extraction workflows.
How could BHL support this kind of work further?
While there are probably very many kinds of relations that are in some way or other
expressed in the historic biodiversity literature, it would be great to
see entity recognition for entity types like persons or named
geographical places already being annotated and linked to norm
data, similar to taxon names.
Also, in the course of this project, we discovered that certain kinds of metadata
that link full texts, bibliographic details within one journal and
between related journals that are not yet included in BHL would be
helpful to discover sources more efficiently.
This work was, of course, a team effort and was made possible through support by
MFN's Innovation Fund. Thank you for your attention.
Thank you. Again, if you do have questions, please put them in the Whova app, and
Christian will answer them during this session, hopefully.
Thank you again, Christian, for your wonderful talk.
I'd now like to introduce Gavin Kasparek.
Thank you very much for your talk.
Thank you.
Okay.
Good afternoon. Thank you very much for the opportunity to present some
general considerations about the data contained in the literature and about
some steps needed to extract this kind of data and about the
challenges. My relation to this topic is
especially my involvement in the project BioFit, but I will
skip the details now because my
talk will be too long, and there will be a separate presentation
about BioFit on Thursday.
So
let's have a look at the data in the literature.
How important is it to mobilize these data?
This has been emphasized, for example, by the Dizentes
roadmap, a very significant step in this regard.
We need more data about historical baselines of
biodiversity, and the literature surely is one of our most
valuable resources for this. But there are a number of challenges
we have to overcome, such as
the high diversity of natural language, the
fact that terminology is not standardized.
There are certain domain-specific practices which make
natural language processing, abbreviated NLP,
even harder than in other domains.
So let's take a closer look at an example from the German
literature.
I just chosen a botanical article published
1969, but for sure, similar
examples in English can easily be found as well in BHL.
So
for OCR errors,
this article has been scanned from a printed volume, so almost
inevitably there will be OCR errors, and for machines, it
will be hard to recognize that
Listera cordata, the species name, is meant
when
there is this kind of error.
Errors in OCR
are very common. The reliability of keyword search
results suffers significantly from poor OCR
quality, and more advanced uses, such as
NLP or named entity recognition, will suffer even more.
You can say there is a propagation of OCR errors
through the stages of NLP.
The problem is not only that the quality of
OCR is often poor, it is also that the
evaluation of OCR quality is not trivial
and has been called challenging by some authors, for example,
Neudecker. So what we need
is not only a further improvement of OCR tools,
but also an improvement of OCR evaluation
tools.
Synonyms are a common challenge.
This case here is quite easy to resolve because we have databases
which can tell that currently the correct name of this orchid species
is Epipactis atrorubens, not Epipactis rubiginosa.
However, there's another special issue here.
The author abbreviated the genus name, and in other genera,
the same abbreviation may also occur.
For example, there is a species of worm, species of fungus, and so on,
which could also be
abbreviated E. rubiginosa. So we need to consider
context to clearly identify which species is meant, and this is
not trivial for computers.
The number of synonyms is huge. Here we see a small selection
of synonyms for this one species, and in many
taxonomic databases, synonyms outnumber
accepted names.
As an example, we can take the plant list, which had
44% synonyms
with only 33% of accepted names.
But not only names change over time.
With many well-known names being reduced to synonyms,
the taxonomic concepts behind the names may also
change, and this is often overlooked.
The same binomial name may refer to different taxonomic
concepts, which may be more or less congruent, but often they
are only partly overlapping. Take the example of the
European oak, Quercus robur. This name was coined by
Linnaeus,
but it had a very different circumscription than Quercus
robur L. in the sense of modern authors.
Nevertheless, modern authors claim it to be a Linnaean
name.
The phenomenon of shifting taxonomic concepts must be taken into
account when extracting data from legacy literature,
which spans centuries of taxonomic change.
And this is far more challenging than mere synonymy
problems.
So in connection with synonymy and homonymy, there are some domain-specific
characteristics, especially in taxonomic texts,
which require special
consideration. Latin modifiers such as sensu,
auctorum, non, nec, propter, and so on, often
show that identical binomial names may refer to different
taxa.
Same example here, Quercus robur sensu
lato often means Linnaeus' broad concept of
Quercus robur, while Quercus robur sensu stricto
could mean the modern narrow concept of this species.
Another aspect is homonymy, of course.
The genus name Liparis is not only a botanical name, but
also a genus of fish is called Liparis.
It's a toponym for a lake in Canada and so on.
A more prominent example of homonymy is Paris, which is a
genus of plant, a city in Texas, a city in France, and so on.
We see that phenomena such as synonymy, homonymy, and shifting
taxon concepts create ambiguity in legacy
literature. What could be the steps to find solutions?
First thing is to develop
even more comprehensive taxonomic backbones to resolve synonymy.
We need then to improve taxonomic entity recognition tools.
We need to incorporate broader context for automatic
taxonomic name disambiguation.
We should enable temporal disambiguation of taxon concepts, which
could mean to capture historical data on the evolution of
concepts, and we should implement or expand, of course,
standards like the Taxon Concept Standard, and
CATWIC, of course, has an important role here.
Next aspect is coreference
resolution. In linguistics, coreferences
occur when two or more expressions refer to the same
object. In this example,
the expressions Coeloglossum viride and Coeloglossum
are shown, and it is clear for human readers that in the
latter case, the author has just dispensed with the longer
designation out of economy, but is nevertheless
referring to the same species, Coeloglossum viride.
And there are many other types of coreferences which are not easy for
computers to resolve.
So for NLP tools, coreferences continue to be a
significant challenge.
Coreferences are common and take many forms, and they may
several sentences or several paragraphs.
And taxon-related coreferences include domain-specific
forms. For example,
as mentioned, C. viride can mean the same as Coeloglossum
viride,
or a mere Coeloglossum can mean the same as Coeloglossum
viride, or a mere var. nanum could
mean Coeloglossum viride var. nanum.
How to cope with coreferences like this?
First, we need to apply state-of-the-art NLP for
general coreference resolutions, including
transformer models, for example, but it will also be
important to integrate domain-specific tools
such as nomenclatural ontologies.
Last aspect here is mixture of languages.
Mixture of languages often occurs in biodiversity
documents. In this example, three languages are mixed.
The paper is in German. There's a Latin diagnosis and also a
specimen citation in English.
In fact, many tools for natural language processing
require prior specification of the language of a document.
Such tools will give poor result.
So it will be necessary to select tools which are able to
detect language on a per sentence or per paragraph
basis. And for low-resource languages like Latin,
we also need special solutions.
So legacy literature holds invaluable biodiversity
data waiting to be unlocked. But here's the challenge:
we can't access it effectively yet due to OCR errors,
synonyms, shifting concepts and so on.
So how do we move forward? I think the answer lies in a
coordinated approach. First, we need technical solutions.
We must advance OCR precision, leverage cutting-edge
NLP, including domain-specific ontologies, and these
tools are the foundation for cleaning and structuring raw data.
Second, we need taxonomic rigor. We need to further
strengthen taxonomic backbones, adopt universal
standards, enable temporal disambiguation.
After all, a name in 1850
may not mean the same today. Our systems must account for that.
So I think this is
a hard way, but the reward would be immense because we would be
able to mobilize
much valuable data with this. Thank you.
Wonderful. Thank you.
I think we'll probably leave questions to the end.
I'd like to introduce Jana Hoffmann from Senckenberg Nature Research.
Jana
used to be at Museum für Naturkunde and was a member there.
She's moved organizations, and now we have an exciting new member in Senckenberg
Nature Research, so we're very excited to welcome Jana back to the BHL community.
She's an absolute treasure to have in the network that's holding BHL up.
Thank you, Jana.
Yeah. Thanks for giving us the opportunity to talk.
I won't give this talk alone. I will have my colleague, Sefika Efeoglu.
She will support me
in presenting our first
results.
Historical biodiversity literature often combines detailed
textual descriptions with very nice illustrations, especially
when they come from historical resources.
But computational methods either process one of these different sources
separately or prefer the text, as we've seen in the previous
presentations. So in this talk, we show how we can maybe connect
those two
to produce structured knowledge and generate evidence-based
captions, because in historical sources often captions for
plates and illustrations are lacking.
So I will briefly introduce our motivation and our case study, our Merian case
study, and then Sefika will walk you through the workflow, and then I will return
to summarize what we have done so far and what we want to do in the future.
So biodiversity knowledge is often multimodal.
We heard that today at several
points in time, and so the text can describe an organism,
can say something about the host plant, or can
report on feeding interactions, for example.
And illustrations, they contribute complementary
evidence, such as morphological appearance.
They can picture developmental stages or provide spatial relations between these
entities.
So, however, as I said before, many of these extraction pipelines that we
know and that are worked on concentrate on OCR and on textual information
alone. And so as a result, we feel like part of the evidence that is there
and contained in illustrations is kind of disregarded.
So our aim is to connect both representations through shared biological concepts.
For example, a caterpillar mentioned in the text, for example, can be
linked to the corresponding image region, and relationships described in the text
can also be compared with what is represented visually.
So what did we test that and how did
we start with that? So our use case or our case or
prototype
source is the Merian book on "Der Raupen wunderbare
Verwandlung und sonderbare Blumen-Nahrung." I can say that because I'm German.
So it's from 1679, so it was published a
long time ago. So this copy of
this historical book is held in the
Senckenberg, a special library for entomology in Münchenberg,
with the catalog number, if you ever wanted to look that up, 877.
And there are 50 very beautiful illustrations with corresponding texts
in this book that you can find. So the first step was for us to
digitize the volume and also provide a digital
edition in 2026
via Zenodo to the community. And this is also our first
case where we want to
provide that for BHL to be ingested to BHL very soon.
So we're working on that. But in the meantime, we also want to use that as a case
study to test some of the things that I talked about before.
So, in the next step,
Sefika will walk you through this.
Firstly, we start by extracting the textual
information
by using the Olmo-OCR. This is the LLM-based OCR,
and then we define the concepts in the ontology.
Afterwards, with this ontology,
we detect the visual entities, their relations, and also the
attributes.
Later, we use these visual entities, relations, and their
attributes to
annotate the text
entities. And
afterwards, we merge the entities in the text, and
also the sticking graph
entities and relations.
At the end, we verbalize the sub-knowledge
graph to generate the captions.
Here you can see
how the-
How we
detect the entities in the illustration.
It has the colors and
shapes and also the location of the butterfly.
It is nearby tulip.
As I said before, we use the visual entities
to annotate the text. Here you can see the relevant
butterfly, tulip, and others in the text, but the
original article in German, so this is just the
illustration.
As I said before, we merged the entities
in the illustration and also the text passages
into the
multimodal sub-knowledge graph.
Here you can see the
trace
life cycles and the
other information about the illustration.
Afterwards, we use this illustration on the selected
turtles to generate the captions.
This generated caption only support
these turtles.
Yeah. So, this is an additional set of captions that we could
produce if we let the models hallucinate a little bit more.
So the previous one that I saw, one of the first test cases,
basically demonstrated really just what was supported, but this one is
where we want to go. But of course, we want these captions to be evidence
grounded and not the hallucinated kind of additional
content.
So, as I said, this is a prototype, so we're
at the point where we have all the content digitized, we have the articles
separated, and we also have the workflow in place so we can do
the
figure caption generation based on a few selected examples.
And now the task will be to do this on the entire corpus
with all the 50
different articles that we have selected.
And of course, do further consolidation and the whole
provenance and documentation part.
And of course, as the next step, and that has been mentioned before in other
presentations, we need the human in the loop.
So we would like to really get our specialists to look at the
retrieved information and check whether this is correct and
also in general, check the accuracy and completeness of
the captions that we have produced.
And the ultimate goal will be to, of course, provide this as a
workflow that can be used for other content, other historical
sources. We talked about that during the BHL annual meeting, that we need
more also downstream examples on how to use the
BHL content at large.
So this is a first demonstrator of a new working group at
Senckenberg, the
Semantic Data Systems and Knowledge Engineering group.
So, be kind with your comments. So we're just starting this,
and we really would like to build on really making entomological
knowledge more available, more accessible for everybody.
So the few takeaways here, just to summarize, text and illustration
provide complementary evidence and should be regarded together.
I think there are more tools and technologies out there now that help us
to achieve that and not just look at the text alone.
We need to create alignment, or alignment creates connected
knowledge. So we want to really get these connections out and also
demonstrate these shared entities and
point out more about the traits and ecological interactions that actually are
contained in these publications.
And of course, we want to build on knowledge graphs that enable the
reuse of the knowledge in the publications themselves
and want to extend this to other collections.
So here you have two QR codes if you're interested in our work.
On the left side, you find the one that is the Merian copy, the
digital edition that you also will find in BHL soon.
And on the other side, it's the QR code
for our workflow documentation, if you're interested in that.
There will be two more talks
from my working group. Vika Efiolu will give a talk in the AI Readiness
Symposium on Thursday about the Croissant standard, and
Marja Timmermans, our data manager, will reflect on her role in our
institution
from the Clouds to Cabinet symposium also on Thursday.
So thanks for having us.
Wonderful. Thank you.
Again, I think we'll hold questions until the end.
Now, love to introduce my long-term colleague, Professor Rod Page.
Lights, camera, action.
Okay.
How should I talk about this? So what I want to do is basically give you a taste
of the workshop, which is on Thursday morning.
The goal of this workshop was basically just to throw at you, as this talk is going
to do, a whole bunch of possible future ways we can
envision BHL, some interfaces.
These are going to be things that most of these are live.
You can come along and play with them.
And I also kind of see it as a way to extend the conversation.
So it's also a chance that if there are things you think BHL really should be
doing, this will be a place to sort of talk about it.
And if some of the demos are interesting We could explore that.
If they're crap, please tell us. I should also say that I'm just doing this
just randomly. I can't make any promises on behalf of BHL that any of this will
happen.
But if you see something you really like, maybe you could then prod them to do
something.
Right. So loads of slides, very quickly.
So BHL, lots of stuff.
So there's a bunch of challenges. So the first, the most obvious one is how you
view content. There's various ways to view stuff.
So in this workshop, we're going to have a look at a few of these.
There is the
classical BHL interface, which hasn't changed
in about 10 years and does not work on my mobile phone, and that
really p****s me off. Maybe you don't care about looking at it on your iPhone.
I kind of do. So there's that kind of approach.
This particular article we're going to see a lot of,
this is this article on the journal website. They use a PDF viewer.
Maybe BHL should just show PDFs.
This is an experimental viewer you've got to play with that actually changes size
depending on whether you're on an iPad or an iPhone.
Is this the kind of thing that we want?
This will toggle between a nice text display and images, so you can have a play
with that.
This one, I don't know if Donata's still here, but PLOS did an
experiment recently where they had a viewer that included all the
annotations. We learned a lot about annotations today.
Do we want to see BHL content like this with lots of things
marked up? So these are all live possibilities we could have a look at.
I'd be interested to see what you think.
Search. Now finding stuff is obviously the next challenge.
We want to figure out how to see it, how do we find stuff.
BHL has various ways of finding things. It has full text search.
I don't know what your experience is. My experience is it's a bit ropey.
This is a search I did for Aphrophila gen nov.
Fairly distinctive phrase.
These are the top four hits. In BHL, you can drill down in each one and
see what it found. And
so there's hit number one, and below it shows you the actual strings that the
things match that, and none of those are Aphrophila gen nov.
Second hit, lots of nov gens and stuff, but not the one I'm looking for.
Number three,
Aphrophila. Number four, yay, we finally got it.
So why is the fourth-best hit the one that I presumably want, the actual one
that matches the string? Search is hard, but we obviously can
do some work on that.
Taxonomic names.
I guess the killer feature for many people is the ability to search BHL by
taxonomic names. The whole thing has been indexed.
Now, this works really well except when it doesn't.
So if you are interested in the genus Scutellum,
good luck, because that's a very well-known part of an insect.
BHL has huge numbers of results, and most of these are anatomical part.
Likewise, there are countries. Argentina is also a taxonomic name.
It doesn't do a really good job of distinguishing between phrases like that.
So what can we do about that?
There are various ways to explore search results.
This will be another little live demo to have a look at.
I've always been obsessed with the idea about how names change over time in BHL.
What you can do here is put in a name or a pair of names
and see how they've changed over time.
If you're a fan of Wikipedia, there's a famous, famous
example of-- this is the sperm whale.
There are two Linnaean names for the sperm whale, and there's a
huge, very foul-mouthed
debate on Wikipedia about which name to use for the page.
And you can go and do a quick search and see how names have changed over
time. Is that useful? Is that something BHL should do? This is live.
You can have a play with it.
We've heard a lot about OCR. I'm going to be slightly
bold about OCR.
So the OCR landscape has changed dramatically in the last few years.
There are now amazing LLMs. This is my favorite.
This is Datalab, which I think is a company in Boston.
Harris talked earlier about particularly Mistral, which is the OCR
engine the museum is using in London.
It is extraordinary what these things can do.
And to give you a sense of this,
so on the left is the OCR for this page in BHL today.
On the right is essentially completely unmodified
OCR for the same article that's come out of Datalab.
That is almost as good as what you'll see in one of Lubo's pencil journals.
I mean, it's pulled out tables, figures, figure captions, the whole lot.
To a first approximation, OCR is solved, and obviously not
entirely, but this is extraordinary.
So the only barrier now is cost.
Geography. This is an area that has been somewhat is a bit neglected,
I guess, in the BHL interface. I want to show you a few ways we can play with that.
Just to give you a sense of what's in there, this is a tiny subset of BHL data.
This is from my BioStore project. This is just
point localities that are mentioned explicitly as latitude and longitude
in content from BHL Australia, hence the Australian map.
So the question then is how do you explore geographic
content in a library?
Do you like that? Which is what GitHub does with it.
Would you like something like this? This is in BioStore.
We can go to a particular area and draw a polygon around it.
So I could say, "Show me papers about Sri Lanka."
You can have more elaborate polygons.
This is actually inspired by a group I met in Davos who wanted to get all the
papers in BHL for every island in the world, and you can essentially
do that. Is that what we want for maps?
The final thing about maps, this is something I stumbled across, is an amazing
project called All Maps, which is basically about putting maps on maps.
So essentially, what you're seeing here, this is a report from an
expedition
And you'll find loads of these in BHL, historical maps.
So where exactly is that? If you wanted to convert that into, say,
point localities for where people went on expedition, you want to stick that on a
map. All maps allows you to do that. So we can have a play with that.
You can actually take some examples from BHL and try and put these
maps, their species distributions, expedition reports.
Is that something that we should support?
You can't do that easily with the current BHL, but it would be kind of fun to do.
Image classification and search.
There's been various sort of attempts to sort of explore this.
Mike Trinsey at the Smithsonian was one of the first.
He came up with a neat little tool, which basically you stick in an image,
and you ask the tool, what kind of thing is this? Is it a plate? Is it text?
Is it blank? Which is a really useful kind of thing to do.
Traditionally, BHL has done that manually.
So inspired by some of the kind of models behind this, we can take this a bit
further.
This is kind of BHL Australia.
I wanted to sort of give you the sense of the kind of content that's in there.
So this is about 200,000 pages, and we are just basically zooming in
and having a look. So there's modern-looking scientific articles,
there's the pretty, there's old historical plates that everybody loves.
There's field reports, all kinds of stuff.
And here it's just arranged bibliographically.
So how would you find particular images that you want in that kind of
corpus?
So I took the very same sort of model that Mike Trinsey used
and classified all these images and made it a little search engine.
Now, again, this is live. You can have a play with this.
This is not for all of BHL, it's just for BHL Australia.
So, for example, you might have a picture of a butterfly.
You can go and search BHL. Does anything look like that?
In fact, you'll find illustrations of exactly that species.
To me, this is kind of like iNaturalist.
It's kind of like you could imagine trying to identify a species
using an image search in BHL.
Here's a plant specimen.
Has anybody published anything on that plant specimen? I'm going to speed up now.
You can actually search for that herbarium specimen, and indeed, yes,
there's a paper that actually reproduces that.
So if you want to find out about that specimen, you can go and look at that paper.
The other thing about this particular model, which is kind of cool, is you don't
need to search with images alone. You can search with text.
So you could search for glacier. It's a fairly hot topic at the moment, given what
happened in Nepal and Tibet. So these are pictures of glaciers.
Phylogenies. We could get some phylogenies.
Realize Joey Miller's goal with having phylogenies in GBIF.
These are potentially interesting kind of trees.
Do you like red flowers? You wanted to search for traits.
These are flowers that are red,
and so on. I could go on endlessly, and I will.
Or you could be sort of more oriented towards BHL tasks.
These are things that look like first pages in articles.
There's a constant challenge to find those articles in BHL. We could do that.
So is this sort of thing useful? Have a play and see what you think.
Okay, we're almost there. There's a couple of things which may or may not happen.
I threw this in. I think, don't know if Cindy's still here, but she keeps
mentioning MCP. I like MCP. This is just a way of having a chatbot
that talks to something. I am hoping we'll have one of these up and running to
talk to BHL by Thursday. So you can experiment with that.
It depends on this,
BHL and RDF, which is a knowledge graph.
In the last two or three weeks, there's been all sorts of extraordinary things
happening. GBIF is now available in RDF.
There's a knowledge graph flying around for GBIF.
It sort of inspired me to think about could you do the same with BHL?
So if we're lucky, we go to talk to BHL and ask it questions.
Okay, so before Nicole drags me off. So these are the main summaries.
So the workshop is, it's live, it's on GitHub.
By all means, come along Thursday morning.
If you can't make it, you can go to that GitHub page and have a look.
All the stuff is there. Most of the demos that I showed you are live and
functioning until people use them.
And what I want to get out of this is what of these kind of things, what, if any of
these things, do you think are useful, you'd like to see in BHL?
Which things are kind of mad toys and we don't care about them?
I'm also interested in thinking about, okay, the things that are of use, how would
we actually make that happen?
Obviously, for BHL, the concern would be which one of those would be the most
important ones to do, and also
the wider community. There are clearly other things going on, and you've seen some
talks this afternoon that we could also make use of that may help
some of this kind of work. So that's the sales pitch.
Thursday morning,
be in whatever room it is on your program. Thanks very much.
Thank you, Rod. A brilliant taster for the workshop on Thursday
morning at 8:30. I don't remember the room either.
And also an extraordinary taster for BHL Australia.
So thank you again for showcasing my project.
My other hat is I manage that project for the whole of Australia.
Does anyone have any questions for any of our speakers today?
Great.
Thank you. It's always a treat to come to BHL sessions and
fantastic talks.
One aspect we often come to
discuss at the BHL sessions at TadWig is that how about gazetteers?
How do we extract all this geographic information?
And there were several mentions of the spatial components today.
If GBIF is RDF and BHL will be in RDF, can we just throw it
everything in Claude and say go, and then use GBIF as a gazetteer
and extract all the geographic information from all these pages?
Again, a provocation. Easy to do after Rod's
presentation.
But
is this
an opportunity
Extracting names and finding a species on the right page has been a key
feature. This is why everybody loves BHL.
But then
dates, I think, will be trivial. But then the locations, all
these Black Rivers and so on, that would be very nice to
extract for real
across all pages. And another
prompt and plug or wish is not only do this with the formally
published literature, but with field journals.
And this is BHL old project. Not maybe everyone remembers it.
I do, and I think it was one of the coolest things you ever did.
With these expedition journals, they are
lines on the maps
where binomial-like annotations of the specimens together with the field notes
can make very cool information graphs.
I think this is what I take out from this wonderful session. Thank you very much.
If there are any reactions, I would be very happy to hear them.
Thank you. Please keep those wonderful ideas and also praise for
BHL coming.
More questions?
So I'm using BHL quite a lot, but for me,
the biggest question was why BHL still doesn't have full
index, all the articles in the journals.
So everything end up as journals and pages, but not the
articles inside of the pages.
Can answer that.
So when we upload content into BHL, we upload at
the volume level with the volume level metadata.
So it'll be volume five of Curtis' Botanical Magazine.
Project began by Biostor,
decade to 2012,
was to try and find those articles.
And so Rod, particularly interested in the taxonomic descriptions, started
uploading article data into BHL.
And I think I said yesterday, 450,000 of those journal
articles now have article data, which makes those discoverable.
In 2000, when we were all locked down, I started working on that project as
well, started leading the Persistent Identifier Working Group, which was
retrospectively assigning DOIs to those articles.
But the huge part of that work was doing the article data.
So Rod does the work at scale. I've been working on the
high-hanging fruit, the articles that are difficult to find.
I have volunteers working on that.
That project was put on hold in April last year,
because we have had to work on making BHL
sustainable and actually moving across from the Smithsonian.
I'm very keen for it to get started again.
My call would be all contributors of content to BHL have to also upload the
article data. It is a huge amount of work to gather it and clean it and get it into
BHL. But yes, it is essential. I almost say to people, "If you don't do
that, you may as well leave your journals collecting dust on the shelf," because
that discoverability is so important.
So it's definitely a core BHL project that I would really like to
continue. At the moment, it's on hold, unfortunately, but we
would hope to start resourcing that again at some point.
It was my baby, and I took it on. Well, Rod and my baby, actually.
But he started it. It's his brainchild.
And we've been working very closely together to do that for a long time.
Yeah, you can follow up on that.
So I guess the simple answer is there's probably about two ways we can get
articles. One is if we had a complete bibliography of life, a list of every
published article in taxonomy, we would run that against BHL, and we
get the articles.
The other approach, which we've never really tried, is essentially
get an AI to read BHL and say, "This is an article page, this is an article
page." And some of the work that Harris was talking about earlier is like that.
So if we had a complete list of every article
or something would read BHL and find them for us, we could do it.
We don't have those two things.
I was surprised it wasn't the default from the very beginning.
I can't speak to that.
Well, you could probably speak to this as well, but BHL was initially a library
project. It was a collection of librarians making that content accessible,
which is still an incredibly important and valuable goal to put content
into BHL and make it accessible online.
The discoverability part of that is, I think, as equally important as
accessibility.
As Rod said, it almost seems ridiculous to be getting volunteers to do this work at
the moment when AI could perhaps scrape it, do it very quickly.
We're very close to being able to do that.
The NHM work is also working on that, so we should hopefully get
there. And Rod, when I say it's on hold, the bit, the core, the
paid work that was involved in that is on hold. Rod is still doing it.
He is a
pirate who just continues to do all the incredible things.
He's whipped up half the tools he showed you this week, and we'll probably have, as
he said, more available by Thursday.
So we just need clever people and probably AI to do more of this.
Any other questions?
Were there any more online or any online?
What I think we're getting the sense of is that BHL is an extraordinary
resource of 64 million pages, and there is so much we can do
with the content, the knowledge, the foundation of our understanding of
biodiversity that has been made available online by all of the
organizations who've been involved in contributing the content, and all the
incredible people and organizations that are now doing things with that content.
We'd love for people to do more things with that content.
The workshop on Thursday will be all about how can we make that
incredible source of information more usable, more accessible, more
connected, more interoperable.
And we're really excited to hear your ideas, and
commitment and
... contributions to that session on Thursday and beyond.
As I've been saying across this conference, if you have ideas, if you have
connections, if you have resources, if you know of billionaires and millionaires,
or if you can think of other exciting new ideas, we've heard people suggest maybe
we need a startup, maybe we need to come to people with figures.
We are new at this. We're new at fundraising, we're new at reaching out
for philanthropy, and
we now need to do that. So I know a lot of organizations are doing the same.
David, do you have any closing words?
Thank you very much, Nicole.
I'd just like to take this opportunity to, A, thank everyone for coming, but also
say a huge thank you to all our speakers today.
But before I say any more, I did want to say a special thank you to Nicole
herself, who has been a fantastic driving force behind this
symposium, and also is frankly one of the reasons
we are in such good stead and rode the storm so
well over the past year from the transition from
Smithsonian. So can we have a huge round of applause both for our speakers and
also Nicole, and thank you.
Thank you very much everyone again for coming.
We are around all week. Do come and find us.
There are a number of BHL champions both in the room and further out in
the conference, as well as representatives from the executive committee,
including Amanda and myself. So, please do come and speak to
us if you have any ideas, suggestions. We're very pleased to hear.
Thank you everyone.